<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the Right Honourable Thomas Lord Osborne, Viscount Latimer, Lord High Treasurer of England Reasons humbly offered to consideration for the erecting of several light-houses upon the north-coast of England, for the security and increase of navigation &amp;c. viz. 1. A double light-house at St. Nicho. Gat. 2. A light-house upon the Stagger-land at Cromer. 3. A light-house upon flambro-head. 4. A light-house upon Fern-Island.</title>
            <author>[Phrip, Richard].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 145 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2137A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218248</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829859</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34305</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34305)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2011:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the Right Honourable Thomas Lord Osborne, Viscount Latimer, Lord High Treasurer of England Reasons humbly offered to consideration for the erecting of several light-houses upon the north-coast of England, for the security and increase of navigation &amp;c. viz. 1. A double light-house at St. Nicho. Gat. 2. A light-house upon the Stagger-land at Cromer. 3. A light-house upon flambro-head. 4. A light-house upon Fern-Island.</title>
                  <author>[Phrip, Richard].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Richard Phrip.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lighthouses --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34305:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34305:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A PROPER LOOKING GLASSE FOR THE DAVGHTERS OF SION OR S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. AVGVSTINES LIFE ABBRIDGED, AND reduced into points of Meditation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVITH MEDITATIONS for a ſpirituall exerciſe at Cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Profeſsions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By THOMAS CARRE their Confeſſour.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>POST NVB F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>T</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>AT PARIS,</p>
                  <p>M.DC.LXV.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34305:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34305:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE 1. MEDITATION.</hi> HOVV HE VVANDERED from his heauenly Fathers hovvſe, and by vvhat degrees.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDER how their was a tyme when this great Saint (him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſing it) being tranſported by the heate of youth, wandered out of his Fathers houſe euen into a land of extreame diſproportion, and that by no other ſtepps or degrees,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34305:3"/>but firſt by idlenes the ſourſe of all euills: heare his owne words: <hi>vvhen I grevv idle at home vvith my parents, the brambles of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte deſires grevv euen ouer my heade.</hi> (Waigh in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar the euils you may haue fallen into by it) ſecondly by ill compaignie <hi>vvhich moues vs,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>often to doe that vvhich vve should neuer doe alone, but vvhenſoeuer it is ſaid, let vs goe, and let vs doe this or that, vve are ashamed, and blush, if vve doe not shevv our ſelues to be paſt shame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION. âh! how true it is, ô friendshippe, that we experience thee, often tymes, too too vnfriendly, nay euen a cruell ſeducer of our ſoules, for that which the Diuell by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34305:3"/>himſelfe cannot, by the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a friend he is able to effect. That deare name of louing and being beloued carries vs quite away to perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And idleneſſe ſerues for nothing but onely to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, and ſuggeſt fewell to this conſuming fire. Say my ſoule, is it no ſo indeed?</p>
                  <p>RESOLVTION. Neuer will I more then intertayne ſuch or ſuch a thing for euer. I renounce you ô vaine and fruiteleſſe thoughts! I abiure you ô friuolous and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble remembrances: I forſake you for ouer vnfaithfull and diſloy all frindships, miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and loſt ſeruices, miſpent gratifications, diſpleaſing and indeed paynefull pleaſures.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34305:4"/>the third ſteppe to Auguſtines ruine, was his neglect of his Mothers counſell, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him but like old wiues fables, which, as he faith, he was ashamed to follow. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how it is euen thus that all our miſeries doe increaſe and ripen. we firſt waxe tepide and idle in Gods ſeruice; we ſpend tyme in imbraceing a maſſe of vaine thoughts and extraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances; we then meete with a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion of the ſame mould, whoſe equall follie doth fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and increaſe our fancie, and by litle and litle we are hurried on to a precipice of miſcheife: Parents and frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds counſells are imployed to preuent our future woe, but are reiected: we are gone for euer, vnleſſe Gods ſpeciall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34305:4"/>grace doe recalle vs!</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION. Yes it is euen thus, ô my ſoule, that we run to ruine. the fancies of idle houres doe truly feede and increaſe our miſeries: and what doth the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch fancies to others, but ſtill more and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon and ripen the deſeaſe of our mynds? and euen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our harts againſt that ſoueraigne remedie, the good Counſell of ſuperiours and friends.</p>
                  <p>RESOLVTION. Againſt idlenes, I will ſtill haue in memorie, that vpon the good or bad vſe of the moments of tyme which we now haue, a happie or accurſed eternitie doth depend: and that a tyme will come that a moment of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34305:5"/>tyme shall not be left to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in. Againſt bad compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, I will remember, that <hi>he vvho toucheth pitch shall be defyled vvith it:</hi> and that <hi>vvith the good vve shall be good; and vvith the peruerſe vve shall be peruerted.</hi> Againſt the neglect of good counſell (which is a thing of ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a conſequence, that the prouerbe aſſures <hi>(paſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell paſt grace)</hi> I will haue theſe ſacred leſſons deeply imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my mynd. <hi>Want and ignominie shall be his share vvho forſakes diſcipline: but glorie to him vvho giues eare to one vvho doth counſell and correct.</hi> Prouerbs c. 13. and Prou. 29. <hi>Soudaine diſtruction shall ouertake, or fall vpon that man vvho vvith a ſtiffe necke
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34305:5"/>contemnes him vvho doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him.</hi> And theſe of S. Auguſtine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thought it vvas onely she vvho ſpoke</hi> (meaning Saint Monica) <hi>but her vvords vvere indeed thyne</hi> (ô God) <hi>and in her perſon, thou vvaſt contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by me. I being old, and a Bishop, am readie to be taught by a child. Petition,</hi> Say with Salomon. Giue me ô Lord a Docile hart, a hart myld and ſupple, and readie to take the good tincture of wholſome counſell.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34305:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE II. MEDITATION.</hi> Whither he vva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, and vvhat miſeries he mett vvithall in his vvandering pilgrimage.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT. COnſider that he follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the ſtepps of the prodigall child, and with him arriued in a foraine Land, whither ſin ledd him, and putt him into ſo great a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from Gods helping hand, that he fell into the hands of theeues: <q>my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> did with me what euer they pleaſed; they beate me, they ſtript me naked, they defyled, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34305:6"/>wounded, and euen killed me, <hi>and all this,</hi> becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe I departed from thee, and becauſe I became a verie nothing without thee.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLVT. Woe be to that audacious ſoule, who by leauing thee (ô Deare Lord) dares preſume to hope to find out any thing els in heauen or in Earth not onely better then thee, or like to thee, but euen any thing tolerable without thee! Thou haſt made vs to, and for thy ſelfe; thou haſt endowed our ſoules with a capaciouſnes capable of thy ſelfe, and our harts muſt needs be vnquiete, till they returne to thee, and repoſe in thee. Be they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken for euer ô Lord, who forſake thee, may their names
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34305:7"/>be written vpon the grownd, that they haue abandoned thee, the veyne of liueing water.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that thoſe enemyes of our good, hauing maymed vs, leaue vs not ſo; but obſeruing that none comes in, to our ſuccour <hi rend="margQuotes">they vilifie and contemne vs, they make their vvay ouer our bellies; they treade vs vnder feete, and with the filth of ſinne defile Gods holy Temple, and leaue vs gaſping vpon the ground, full of deſolation, and worne out with ſorrow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFEC. and RESOL. This ſad truth Bleſſed Auguſtine fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not to publish in the eares of all the world; and wee frequently fayle not to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34305:7"/>experience in owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, if we make reflection, and yet alas, we endeuour not in good earneſt to flie from the face of ſo cruell a foe, but euen without witt or feare, we trudge after them, being blind and naked and loaden with the chaynes of our ſinns. <hi>They vvounded me and I gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not: they haled and trayled me after them, and I vvas not ſenſible of it!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that Auguſtins and our miſeries find yet no periode; but growe vp to a higher exceſſe. We doe not onely by our flight from God fall into the power of our deadely foes, are ſtript, and wounded by them, (while yet we follow them without feare, and grow ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſileſſe)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34305:8"/>but we euen fall in loue with our miſerie, misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and ſeruitude. <hi>I vvas ſlaue and yet loued my ſlauerie: blind and yet deſired my blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> In a word, <hi>to me bitter ſeemed ſvveet, and ſvveet bitter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFEC. and RESOLVT. A pittifull caſe! and yet this is the moſt comon and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deſeaſe, of the banished ſons of Eue. For who knowes not the eye which ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and inticeth vs to ſinne, and yet who hath the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to pull it out: Who ſees not the hand which leads vs to iniquitie, and yet who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues to cutt it off indeed, I meane the companions and occaſions of euil; nay we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and hugge them, and ſeeme to haue our hart ſliced
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34305:8"/>in peeces if we be deuided from them. O how ſtrangly peruerſe, and ſenſeleſly mad is the hart of man? <hi>Make a firme Reſolution of a contrarie proceeding.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE III. MEDITATION</hi> A CONTINVATION OF the ſame ſubiect.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that we are not ſenſeleſſe of our euil onely, and fall in loue with our miſerie, but <hi>from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſenes of the ſame loue grovves luſt; by often yealding to luſt vve make a cuſtome; and by not oppoſing to this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34305:9"/>cuſtome</hi> (which is a certaine law of ſinne) <hi>vve grovv ſubiect to a kind of neceſsitie, vvherby the mynd of man (euen not vvilling) is dravvne and held as in chaynes, in bitter ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Thus farre was our Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne gone, being carried downe by thoſe ſtepps, euen to the verie bottome of Hell. And hither doe we alſo but too often finde our ſelues borne downe by the force of the ſtreame. But oh what a labour had he, and haue we, to row backe againe? how did he turne and wind himſelfe to breake his chaynes, and yet was ſtill deteyned, and was ſuſpended betwixt a dying to death, and a liuing to life:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34305:9"/>whilſt he ſo feared leaſt he should be deliuered from all impediments, as he ought to haue feared the being hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them: whilſt begging for chaſtitie, he was aſtrayd to be heard, leaſt he should haue bene inſtantly deliuered from the deſeaſe of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence. Whilſt the violent cuſtome of ſinne shooke the garment of his ſoule made of flesh and blood, and ſpoke ſoftly to him in this ſort. Is it poſſible that thou canſt thus diſmiſſe vs? And from this inſtant shall we neuer more be with thee? And from this inſtant shall it neuer more be lawfull for thee, to doe this, or that, any more for euer?</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34305:10"/>while the violence of bad cuſtome kept him captiue in ſins Gaole, he mett with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but extreame miſerie want, and famine. His noble and vaſte vnderſtanding was <hi rend="margQuotes">afforded nothing but huskes of ſwine to feed vpon, (and yet was barred to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied euen with ſuch trash) thas is idle perſwaſions of God and godly things, emptie fancies, glorious fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which were ſerued vp deuoyde of that truth which alone is able to ſaciate it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOR. Alas how often doe we hope to feed and fill our ſelues with ſuch like trash, in lieu of ſolide and ſaciating truth, and we are therby onely puffed vp and ſwelled with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34305:10"/>the wind and ſmoke of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: which happens as often as we deſire rather to appeare knowing then well doing; or aſpire to high things aboue vs, with the neglect of the more profitable knowledge of our ſelues. Let me know thee, ô thou, who knoweſt me, let me know thee, and know my ſelfe and let all other knowledges which lead not to theſe, vanish like ſmoke.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that as his vnderſtanding diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered no true light while he liued amidſt that ſeruile darkenes, but was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought with the inquirie of <hi>Truth</hi> without attayning to the knowledge therof, ſo did his will racke it ſelfe to meet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34305:11"/>with and inioye <hi>Good,</hi> and yet could onely light on vnreſt <hi rend="margQuotes">and diſquiete. My ſoule hath turned and toſſed it ſelfe vp and downe, vpon the backe, vpon the ſides, and vpon the breaſt, and it hath found all things hard. For when I grew to obteyne my vnchaſte deſires, in the midſt of my iollitie, I was tyed by miſerable chaynes, that ſo I might be beaten with the burning rodds of iealouſies, ſuſpicions, feares, angers, brawles, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. And ô God how good thou wert to him, and how good thou art to vs in ſo doing, while being mercifully cruell, thou ſprinkleſt all our vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleaſures with extreame
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34305:11"/>diſguſts, (that ſo we may be drawne to the deſire of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king true pleaſures which haue no mixture of diſguſts) ſo that we can find no perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent reſt euen in the moſt proſperous delights the world can boaſt. What meane we then ſtill to trauaile and trudge on through theſe hard and paynefull wayes, where by one torment we purchace another: for we ſee and feele that the burden of ſinne doth certainely and heauily op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe vs. We will therfore returne into our owne harts, and be reconciled and vnited to him that made vs; we will ſtand with him that we may ſtand faſt; and repoſe in him, that we may be truly at reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34305:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE IV. MEDITATION.</hi> Hovv he returned to his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers houſe, and by vvhat ſtepps.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that if <hi>Idlenes, bad compagnie,</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of good counſell,</hi> did vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately lead our B. Saint from his Fathers houſe; he returned as happily backe againe by the quite contrarie ſtepps. Run but ouer in your mynd the innumerable Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes and volumes which he wrote, and you will be ſo farr from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing he could be idle, that you will much
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34305:12"/>wonder when he could find tyme (the actions neceſſarie to his function, as preaching praying, &amp;c. and the tyme ſpent in acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modating neigh bour-iarrs being conſidered) euen, in a manner, to write them ouer, if you did not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by himſelfe, that he was forced to ſteale it from his reſt. <q>I droue two workes at once, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the one by day, the other by night tyme, when other imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments crouding in vpon me on all ſides, did euen permitt me ſo to doe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION, &amp;c. See my ſoule, ſee, how now no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is miſpent, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily by the good imployment of tyme, he redeemes loſt tyme. The day is not enough
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34305:13"/>to pay the malice of his loſt dayes, but the night muſt contribute to it too. He takes the buſines of the whole world vpon his shoulders. He eſpouſeth the ſolicitude of all the Churches with Saint Paule. and all his tyme is ſpent in putting a helping hand to their aggreeuances.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that as he imployed an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good husbanding of tyme to recouer tyme loſt, ſo doth hefly to good companie and counſell for a remedie againſt the infection of the badd companie, and the neglect of good counſell which he had vſed. To Saint Ambrofe firſt, who plentifully diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed antidores or counterpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt the infections of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34305:13"/>bad companie and counſell. or rather ſtarued him with emptie huskes: Saint Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe fedd and filled him with <hi>the flovver of Gods vvheate</hi> which doth fatten: Wheras that made him ſtubborne and ſtiff necked: S. Ambroſe brought him to be ſupple and tractable, <hi>vvith the ſmoothnes of Gods oyle.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as that, with vennimous cupps did intoxicate him. Saint Ambroſe with <hi>the ſober delight of Gods</hi> wine beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teing virgins, doth ingage his hart and regayne him. Next to Simplicianus, Saint Ambroſe his Father, and to Potitianus, who recounting to him Saint Anthonies life which did ſo touch him at the hart, that he forceably
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34305:14"/>cryed out. <q>The vnlearned men of the world doe teare heauen out of our hands, and we with our great knowledge, without braynes or courrage, are ſtill content to wallow in flesh and bloud.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION. And why doe not we, my ſoule, obſeruing in our ſelues the ſame errours, make vſe of the ſame reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies? why doe we not fly the occaſions of euill, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily lay hold vpon the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of good compagnie, and good counſell? If in the one we meete with a moment of falſe delight, experience aſſures vs it is payd with houres, and dayes and yeares of diſcomfort and remorſe of conſcience, wheras in that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34305:14"/>other we might euen here below haue ſome participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heauen, and be left with our thoughts full of a ſolide and permanent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>MEDITATION V. WHAT BEFELL HIM ſoone after his perfect conuerſion to God.</head>
                  <head type="sub">To vvitt a change vvrought by the hand of the highest.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider a ſoudaine and ſtrange change of the hand of the higheſt, which happens to all who abſolut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34305:15"/>conuert themſelues to God. <q>It became ſweete to me, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> to be depriued of the ſweetnes of wordly toyes. What formerly I feared to looſe, I now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from with ioy: For thou didſt caſt them from me, thou ô Lord, who art my true and prime ſweetnes. Thou threweſt them out, I ſay, and in lieu of them didſt thy ſelfe enter, who art ſweeter then all delightes (though not to fleshe and bloode) more ſublime and high then all honour, but not to thoſe who are high in their owne conceipt.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION. Take cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage then, ô my ſoule, take courrage, God is not Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtins God alone, but ours
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34305:15"/>alſo: the bowells of his fatherly mercy lyes open euen to vs too. His loue is not leſſened, his arme is not shortened, Lets but in good earneſt conuert our ſelues vnto him, and his goodnes cannot auert himſelfe from vs. <hi>Be conuerted to me, and I vvill be conuerted to you ſaith our Lord.</hi> Let's but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely diſpoſſeſſe our ſelues of the world and worldly toyes, and he will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falliby inhabite our harts, poſſeſſe them of heauenly ioyes, and make vs expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience a deare and delightfull change.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that he was reſtored to the libertie which by the ſlauerie of ſinne he had loſt.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34305:16"/>
                     <q>Now, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> was my mynd freed from the biting cares, both of honor and riches, as alſo from procuring to welter in carnall ſins, and prouoking the heate of luſt.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Oh what a change is this from that wherin he formerly found himſelfe ingaged, <q>when he ſaid, now all the arguments which I was wonte to bring, were ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and their remayned onely a ſpeachles trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling: and it (his ſoule) feared euen as death it ſelfe, to be reſtrayned from the courſe and fluxe it had longe taken towards ſinne, wherby it was dayly pining away, and growing neerer to deſtruction. And againe I
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34305:16"/>turned and winded my ſelfe in my chayne, till ſuch tyme as that litle which helde me, might be broken; but ſtill it helde me. I was ſaying I would doe it, and euen almoſt did it, yet indeed I did it not, but remayned breathing neere the place, where I should haue bene.</q> We often my ſoule find the ſame wraſtling with flesh and blood, but lets be faithfull to Gods inſpirations, and we shall alſo be reſtored to the ſame libertie.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider thirdly, that as he is more and more remoued from the troubles and cares of the world, he approcheth neerer and neerer to the deare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of heauen, and inioying
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34305:17"/>the true libertie of the ſons of God, <q>I conuerſed, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> in a familiar and tender manner, with thee, who art my beautie, my riches, my ſaluation, my Lord and my God.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESOL. Marke ô my ſoule the delightfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of this heauenly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge We are firſt touched and excited by grace being fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len; we are carried on by delight being riſen; accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payned by delight we are lead to libertie, which affords vs wings of holy deſire to flye vp and repoſe in the boſome of our dearely beloued, and shelter and ſolace our ſelues betwixt thoſe ſacred breaſtes of conſolation, to which I will cling and nothing shall
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34305:17"/>be able to ſeparate me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE VI. MEDITATION</hi> Hovv abſolutely he betooke him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to a good life.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that no ſooner was he reſtored to this bleſſed libertie; and had he receaued the Sacraments at Saint Ambroſe his hands, but he began to lay the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a holy life, by <q>bidding a moſt abſolute Adieu, from the verie bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tom of his hart, <hi>(as ſaith Poſsidius)</hi> to all worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, nether now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireing a wife nor ſons of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34305:18"/>his body, nor riches, nor worldly honors; but made a firme purpoſe to giue himſelfe wholy to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, faſting, prayer and good workes, meditating day and night in the law of our Lord. ſaith Poſſidius.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTIONS and RESOL. O my ſoule lets vs take the ſame reſolution, and humbly confidently and perſeuerant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make vſe of the ſame meanes, and we shall not fayle happily to be reſtored to Gods fauour. He who made vs without vs, will not ſaue vs without our conſent and cooperation. we muſt worke then, not we alone, but Gods grace with vs.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that this reſolution being taken
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34305:18"/>in generall, he found no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way to ſett vpon it in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, then by ſelling what he had, and giuing it to the poore to follow Chriſte: take his owne word for it. <q>I (<hi>ſaith he Epiſ.</hi> 89.) Who write theſe things, did vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently loue that perfection, wherof our Lord ſpoke when he ſaid to the rich young man in the Goſpell. <hi>Goe &amp;c.</hi> and I imbraced it, not by myne owne ſtrength, but by the aſſiſtance of his grace.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Behold ô my ſoule how thy holy Patron ſprings on in the wayes of Gods counſells. Their is now no more cold cras craſes to morow and to morow heard, but fourth with
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34305:19"/>he ſetts vpon it. No more halfe wills wherof the one ſerues to deſtroye the other but he reſolutely, <hi>and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menly loues it.</hi> No more irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, as fearing into what hands he might putt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or that he might looſe by the bargaine, but <hi>he ſells and giues all that he hath.</hi> If we find our ſelues thus affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, how good reaſon haue we to reioyce in our Lord, but if contrarily, we be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying, cold, irreſolute, in what we haue vndertaken, how good reaſon haue we to ſpurre our ſelues on by his example. I will therfore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that he did not build woode, haye, or ſtubble, that is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reane preferments or reſpects
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34305:19"/>of flesh and blood vpon theſe holy fundations, but euen gold, ſiluer, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones, (ſaith Poſſidius) that is, the moſt choyce chriſtian vertues: to witt a feruent loue of God, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>gold;</hi> the loue of the neighbour ſignified by <hi>ſiluer,</hi> and all the reſt of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, imported by <hi>pretious ſtones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESOL. This is the paterne which our holy Patron left vs, let's examine how well we take it out. Is it thus indeed ô my ſoule that we build? Or rather doe we not heape negligences, tepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, vanities, and impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of intention vpon the good fundation we haue layd? Are we not in verie
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34305:20"/>deed cold and ſlowe in the loue of God, and ther vpon, as careleſſe of our neighbour, as though the care of him, had not at all bene com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs? Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for in imitation of our good Patron ſay with him. Giue me, ô Lord, to loue thee, as much as I deſire, and as much as I ought: and my neighbour for thee and in thee, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:34305:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE VII. MEDITATION.</hi> Hovv he behaued himſelfe in Faith.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that he putt down with Saint Paule, whoſe beſt ſcholler he was, <q>that Faith is the ſubſtance of things to be hoped for, an argument of things not appearing. <hi>or, as he ſaith in another place,</hi> it is the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all good things, the verie begining of mans ſaluation. It is an illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mynd, by which it is illuminated by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34305:21"/>Light, to diſcerne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Doe we ô my ſoule, ayme at the true knowledge of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things? doe we deſire our ſaluation, or hope we for thoſe eternall waights of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, thoſe ineffable things which appeare not to the eye; ſound not to the eare, nor enter into the hart of man, which God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thoſe that loue him? know then that it is by the benefit of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly light of Faith. That is the illumination, that, the fundation, that, the very ſubſtance and ſomme of all.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that he putt downe for his ſeconde ground, with the ſame
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34305:21"/>Apoſtle, that without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. <q>I ſaith he, none shall be admitted into the number of the ſons of God without it, <hi>None</hi> without it shall obtayne iuſtifying grace in this world, nor poſſeſſe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life in the next, which is giuen to the loue of God alone.</q> Nor can any loue, whom he knowes not, nor doth any know God, but he to whom it is reuealed by the Father, through faith in his onely ſon Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If without Faith we know not, without knowledge we loue not, without loue we remayne in the iawes of death; if in death there be no grace, nor without grace any hope of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34305:22"/>glorie: If we haue no right to the denomination of ſons, nor conſequently iuſt Title, of Heyres. Oh of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration ought faith to be with vs, how conſtantly ought we to imbrace it, how carefully to conſerue it? For alas, if we miſſe to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered amongſt the ſons of God, we shall not miſſe to be counted amongſt the ſlaues of the Diuell.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him, that <hi>the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of our faith is from Chriſt, from vvhom, by vvhom and in vvhom are all things.</hi> It is not bought by our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; procured by our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtries, or giuen to our merits; but is a pure and free gift of Gods mercy to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34305:22"/>which he is nether neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor induced, ſaue onely by the abundance of his owne vncompelled goodnes.</p>
                  <p>AFF. and RES. Bleſſed be thy goodnes for euer, ô my Lord God, who daynedſt me with this great gift, whilſt I nether deſerued, nor deſired, nor euen thought of it. Farre be it from me to extolle my ſelfe, to arrogate it to my ſelf, as though I had had it of my ſelfe. Nay contrarily vpon the thought of that ſingular goodnes, I fall downe proſtrate before thy Maieſtie pronunceing in all humilitie, <hi>that he vvho doth glorie should glorie in our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34305:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE VIII. MEDITAT.</hi> A CONTINVATION OF the ſame ſubiect.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that though the begining of our faith be from God purely, and cannot be merited by vs, yet is the increaſe of it, (Gods grace being alwayes preſuppoſed) left in our hands to be procured, by care and cultiuating, and by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually accompaigning it with <q>good workes. We are not, to be as it were ſecure in faith, but we are to accompaignie a right faith with a right
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34305:23"/>life. The Apoſtles, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> had not left all, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the hopes of the world, had they not had ſome faith: nor would they haue ſaid, <hi>Increaſe our faith,</hi> had it alreadie bene perfect.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Bleſſed be our good God, who doth not onely preuent vs with his benedictions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we deſerue, or yet thinke of them; but alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues vs power by concurring with his grace, to multiplie his good gifts, yea he hath euen charged vs to negotiate vpon them till he come. Lets vs not therfore be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our ſelues, ſince the increaſe is left in our owne hands.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34305:24"/>though it be our part to make good vſe of the good Talent which Gods grace freely beſtowed vpon vs, and by that good vſe to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie it, yet are we to know with our Saint, <hi>that as no man is ſufficient of himſelfe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin or perfect any good vvorke; ſo is none of himſelfe able to begin or perfect faith.</hi> But the increaſe and perfection of it ought to be procured by our feruent and frequent prayers to the good Giuer, ſaying.</p>
                  <p>AFFBCION and RESOLV. I beeſeech thee, and in a moſt ſuppliant manner I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore thy mercy (ô God who are the fountaine and ſourſe of all good things, the giuer and conſeruer of all vertues) increaſe in me holy, right,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34305:24"/>and immaculate Faith. And make me performe workes ſutable to it, leaſt a good faith may be defiled by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane workes, and leaſt I may deny thee, by a bad life, whom I confeſſe by a good beleife. <hi>I beleeue,</hi> ô Lord, <hi>Yet helpe my increadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your holy Fa. that for want of good workes and feruent and frequent prayers, our Faith, in lieu of increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, falls into a deficiencie; <q>it ſleeps, waxes weeke and ſicklie, yea dyes. Ieſus ſome tymes ſleeps in vs, (as he ſlept in the shippe) that is, our faith which is from Ieſus ſleeps in vs, and then the winds and waues of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34305:25"/>temptation toſſe vs too and fro. <hi>We muſt therfore</hi> awake Ieſus, and the tempeſt shall be allayed, that is, we muſt recollect our faith, and call it to practlſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. <hi>vve perish ô Lord vve perish, haue mercy vpon vs.</hi> For alas why doth our faith ſleepe, but for want of being exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſtirred vp by feruent prayers? whence is it weeke and ſickly, but for want of the nourishement of good workes? whence is it dead but that it is not quickned by charitie? We wil therfore Pray, worke, endeuour to loue God aboue all things, and our neighbour as our ſelfe, &amp;c. and when all is done, we will aſcribe all, not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34305:25"/>to our owne ſtrength, but to Gods grace.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE IX. MEDITATION.</hi> With vvhat modeſtie and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie he looked vpon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith. And hovv high a rate he putts vpon it.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that he aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures not to diue into the knowledge of high mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries with hereticall pride and preſumption, as though witt were able to make way to all; but by a truly Catholike ſubmiſſion and modeſtie, vpon many occaſions, he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34305:26"/>makes open profeſſion of his ignorance; acknowledges the difficultie to be great; knocks hard to haue helpe from heauen; putts downe for a caueat, <hi>to all,</hi> 
                     <q>that it is better to be ignorant with ſafetie, then knowing with danger; <hi>And,</hi> that vnleſſe we beleeue humbly, we shall not ſee clearely.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Let vs beware, my ſoule, of bearing our heads too high, and of being proudely wiſe let vs be wiſe with ſo brietie, it is to the ſimple and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble litle ones that God giues grace, and reueales miſteries shutt vp from the wiſe of the world, who vanish in their owne ſenſe, and reputing themſelues wiſe, are indeed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34305:26"/>
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">fooles. It is the ſimplicitie of beleeuing, not the viua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of vnderſtanding, which ſaues the troupes of Chriſtians.</hi> Low layd then, ô Lord, in my poore nothing, humbly will I expect from thee, the knowledge of ſuch truthes, as thy wiſdome may ſee neceſſarie for thy glorie, and my eternall good. This is all I need, and all I deſire.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider the excellences and fruites of Faith, wherof the firſt is, that it makes the humble and ſimple man, ſee the moſt hidden miſteries, though with an obſcure light, perfectly and infallibly, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation heſitation or doubt <q>at all, Faith hath indeed eyes, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> yea eyes both
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34305:27"/>greater, ſtronger, and more powerfull: eyes which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deceaued any; eyes which are alwayes fixed vpon our Lord: eyes finally which in ſome ſort ſees that to be true which as yet she ſees not: and wherby she moſt certainly ſees, that she doth not yet ſee what she beleeues.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Who are not content with theſe eyes, haue, deſeruedly, eyes, and ſee not, yea with open eyes run to their deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction, and deſcend into Hell aliue, becauſe they would preferre their witt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the infallible guidance of Faith, which was the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per guide giuen vs by God to direct our ſtepps in Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tianitie.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34305:27"/>O moſt bleſſed light, who art not ſeene, ſaue onely by moſt purifyed eyes, puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thes eyes of myne, that flying vanitie, they may dwel vpon VERITIE, and <hi>in thy light ſee light</hi> indeed.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that a ſeconde excellence of faith <hi rend="margQuotes">is, that it is the iuſt mans foode, or his iuſtice: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if he beleeues, he vſeth precaution; if he vſe precaution, he alſo begins to vſe endeuour: and God knowes his endeuour, and lookes into his will, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues his combat with the flesh: exhorts him to fight, helps him to ouercome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects him ſtrugling, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports him falling, crownes him ouercoming.</hi> O how
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34305:28"/>excellent a fruite of Faith is this!</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION. and RESOLVT. Grant, ô Lord, that this Faith, which is the iuſt mans foode and life, may alwayes be found in me ſo vigourous and liuely, that by a wiſe precaution or fore-ſight, I may looke ouer temporall, and fixe vpon eternall things. For thoſe, vſe my beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours; vpon the purchace of thoſe, to ſpend my ſubſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for the attayning of thoſe, to fight lawfully in his ſight, who, after that good combat, and conſeruation of faith, will beſtow vpon me that crowne of iuſtice which (the ſame faith aſſuring) is layd vp for me, and ſuch as loue his coming.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34305:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE X. MEDITATION.</hi> A continuation of the fruites and excellencies of Faith.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider, as a third ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of Faith, that <hi rend="margQuotes">their are no greater riches, no greater treaſures, no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors no ſubſtance of this world greater then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith, which ſaues ſinners, inlighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the blind, cures the infirme, baptiſeth the Cathecumenes, iuſtifies the faithfull, repaires the penitent, increaſeth the iuſt, crownes Martirs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34305:29"/>Virgins, widowes, wiues in puritie, orders clarkes, conſecrates Prieſts, prepars vs to the Kingdome of heauen, and makes vs partake with the Angells in that eternall inheritance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. See then my ſoule, how when we thinke to haue left all, we poſſeſſe all: nay while we thinke to haue loſt all by perſequution we inioy all more happily, while our Faith, which is the greateſt riches, honor, ſubſtance of this world, is not impaired but increaſed by it. They may robbe vs of our riches, yet while our faith is firme they touch not that <hi>aurum optimum,</hi> which is Charitie; They may depriue vs of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34305:29"/>wordly honors, but not of that noble title of being the ſons of God; They may order our ſubſtance to new Maſters, but they cannot quelle our expectation, and hope of <hi>a better and permanent ſubſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider yet further that it is <hi>Chriſtian faith,</hi> which doth rayſe our thoughts, <hi>and conduct vs to the verie highth or topp of</hi> WISDOME AND TRVTH, <hi>the fruition vvherof is no other thing, then bleſſed life or</hi> BEATITVDE <hi>vvhich is neuer found ſaue onely in the diſcipline of our Catholike Mother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If Beatitude be that which all men inceſſantly ſeeke for,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34305:30"/>and not finding can neuer reſt; if it can neuer be found ſaue by the benefit of Faith alone, and faith can noe way be procured but by Gods free gift. What millions of prayſes doe we owe to that infinite Goodnes, who freely beſtowed this incomparable great gift of Faith vpon vs, which inables vs to ſee all good things? O how many <hi>hovv many vvould haue vvis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed to haue ſeene vvhat vve haue ſeene, and haue not ſeene it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Benedicam Domino in omni tempore ſemper laus eius in ore meo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider for the laſt fruite or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, that though this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike faith Eagle-like is able to flie right vp and fixe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34305:30"/>thoſe ſtronge and vndazeled eyes of hers vpon the ſun it ſelfe, and euen gaze vpon Maieſtie; without being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by glorie, yet doth <hi rend="margQuotes">she graciouſly accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date her ſelfe to euery ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie, be they litle, be they great, be they weake be they ſtronge, she hath foode wherwith to nourish them, to ſaciate them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Yes heauenly father, becauſe ſo it was pleaſing in thy ſight. Theſe things thou didſt hide from the prudent and wiſe of the world, and haſt reuealed them to the litle ones, to thoſe litle ones who ſeeke thee in ſimplicitie and humilitie of hart. The wiſeſt (if they be wiſe indeed, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34305:31"/>walke not in wonders aboue them ſelues, and ſo vanish in their owne preſumption) muſt be forced to make their reaſon ſtoope in obedience to Faith, humbly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Credo,</hi> I beleeue what I am not able by witt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer. And the leaſt and ſimpleſt of the children of God, doth no leſſe. ô diuine faith how excellent a Miſtriſſe thou art who in a moment canſt perſuade vs more whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome truthes then all the Ariſtotles in an Age.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:34305:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XI. MEDITATION.</hi> Hovv he behaued himſelfe in Hope, and vvhat motiues he had to imbrace it.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider with Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, that <hi>Faith</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed shewes vs faire things, and ſuch as are worthy of all labour to obteyne them; Yet had we no <hi>Hope</hi> at all, whereby we might be inabled, as well to obteyne them, as to know them, we should ether not att all, or at leaſt, verie weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue the things, which by faith we diſcouer to be ſo beautifull. His faith was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34305:32"/>acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paigned with hope, <hi>vvhich is no other thing, then that, vvherby a man is encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to arriue at that vvhich he beleeues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECT. and RESOLVT. Bleſſed be our good God, who doth not alone freely and without obligation or debt beſtowe a power vpon vs, by Faith to ſee all good things a farre off, but by Hope maketh them in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſent, and as certaine as though alreadie poſſeſſed. Thou doſt not onely giue vs a ſight, and by that ſight begetſt in vs an appetite of a moſt excellent GOOD, but doſt poſſeſſe vs alſo with a certaine expectation, of that future BEATITVDE, grounded vpon thy grace,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34305:32"/>and our owne merits by the ayde there of.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider with the ſame ſaint how our Hope is to be grounded and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vs, and you will find that it is to be done by a good conſcience. <hi>Let him,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>vvho hopes for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of heauen, <hi>haue a good conſcience, and to haue a good conſcience, let him beleeue and vvorke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Let vs not then, ô my ſoule, remayne ſecure in the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge we haue of God by Faith; nor in the ſtrong confidence we haue to obtayne it by the helpe of Hope; but let vs, further, in good earneſt, putt our hand to the worke, leaſt a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34305:33"/>good Faith and Hope, turne our aduerſaries and confound vs, while we produce no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions proportionable to the infallible light, and certaine expectation which we had, by Gods gifts, which were not to be buried.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider whervpon we are to fixe our Hope, and he will tell vs, <q>that it is not to be placed, in preſent things, for they poſt on to paſſe by; nor in aduerſitie, a kind of death; nor in proſperitie, for that is deceiptfully fawning; not in the whole earth, ſince we ſee that is turned topſie turuey, and is in a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall agitation; not in man, nor conſequently in ones ſelfe, ſince we are but men.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34305:33"/>
                        <hi>Where then,</hi> Tranſcende thy ſelfe, and put thy ſelfe in his hands who made thee.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFEC. and RESOL. Alas no, our hopes are not fixed, but toſſed while they are placed vpon ſublunarie and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie things, which are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to a perpetuall viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and change, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which is placed vpon them, muſt needs be ſubiect to the ſame motion and alteration. Where are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights vpon which yeſterday we placed our Hopes? I ſay not where will they be when the world is paſt with its concupiſcence; but where are they euen now, one moment after the poſſeſſion? Where are they? Yeſterday is turned
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34305:34"/>out of dores by this day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; this preſent moment is pushed away by a ſucceeding one, and with it, that is ſnach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from vs wheron our deareſt hopes were fixed, wherwith we thought to haue fedd, but indeed famished, our decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hart. In thee therfore, ô Lord, from henceforth, will I repoſe my whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, and I will not be confounded for euer; Thou art that vnchangeable Good which is aboundantly ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorie and yet art ſubiect to no change. Thou art that Truth, which can nether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue nor be deceiued.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:34305:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XII. MEDITATION</hi> What Chriſtians are to hope for in this vvorld.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that if we be true Chriſtians indeed, <hi rend="margQuotes">we ought to expect for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world but preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and perſequutions wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout hope of better tymes, being aſſured, by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that in the latter dayes many euils, ſcandalls, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and iniquities shall abounde.</hi> This is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our preſent ſtate and vocation, that therby being wayned from the loue of this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34305:35"/>world, our hopes might be wholy ſett vpon a better.</p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESI.. What we ſuffer then, is no ſurpriſe made vpon vs, how ſtrangly ſoeuer we looke vpon it. It is but the ignorance, or not reflection, of what we are, or ought to be, which makes vs impatient of our preſent condition. We are Chriſtians, my ſoule, we were admitted vpon no other condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then to be followers of Chriſt. If they perſequuted him they will perſequute vs too. The ſeruant is not greater then the Maſter. Truth deceaued vs not when he foretold vs, and willed vs to remember that he had foretold vs ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that for his ſake, the world should hate vs, that for his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34305:35"/>name we should be lead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Kings, &amp;c. Nor can he deceaue vs when he ſaith. <hi>Bleſſed be they that ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequution, &amp;c. becauſe theirs is the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that if in the midſt of thes tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and preſſures we lodge our confidence in the boſome of Gods prouidence, or in <hi rend="margQuotes"> the wounds of our Sauiours ſide, not man nor diuell will be able to hurt vs; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one nor the other doth any thing but what God permitts them; nor doth he permitt them to attempt any thing againſt vs but for our aduantage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. In thee, ô Lord, will I hope, and I will not be confounded
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34305:36"/>for euer. I will logde, as in an impregnable Caſtle, in the ſacred holes of thy ſide, there will I repoſe without feare, there will I ſecurely ſleepe. If the wicked make warre againſt me, in this I hope. If the flesh make head againſt me, to this will I flie: If the Diuell barke and bale before my hart, by theſe holes will I haue recourſe to the hart of my Sauiour; he will be with vs in the midſt of our tribulations, becauſe we call vpon him, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer vs and glorifie vs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plenish vs with the length of dayes, and shew vs his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Hence lets conſider, and euen putt <hi rend="margQuotes">downe. and print in a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34305:36"/>hart for a prime and infallible truth, that we Chriſtians were not made for the world; nor for the goods of the tyme preſent, nor for that bewitching fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie which makes men forgett God: but for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine happines, which God promiſeth for the preſent, but man is not now capable of: becauſe of it is ſaid. Nether eye hath ſeene &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Alas no my hart, nether are theſe momentarie Goods which we ſee our true Goods: nor theſe euils which we ſuffer our euils indeede. No: for of theſe goods we ſee the wicked moſt plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully poſſeſſed: with theſe euils we ſee the iuſt moſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34305:37"/>powerfully oppreſſed. Our Good indeed is the cheife Good, that onely, we are to hope for, that to loue alone: and our euil too is the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne euil, that alone we are to feare and flie. Whence we are warned <hi>not to feare them that can onely kill the bodie, and can reach no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but to feare him, vvho can caſte both body and ſoule into eternall fire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34305:37"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XIII. MEDITAT.</hi> What motiues he tooke to confirme Hope.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that the firſt motiue of our Hope, yea euen the ſourſe of all our motiues, is the infinite <hi>goodnes</hi> and Charitie of God, wherby he was moued to conuerſe amongſt vs. <hi rend="margQuotes">We ought not to be without Hope, but rather to preſume in Chriſt with a great confidence; becauſe if through charitie he is with vs in earth, by the ſame charitie we are with him in heauen, according
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34305:38"/>to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Your life is hidden vvith Chriſt in God.</hi> Therfore he is yet below: we are alreadie aboue: He below by the compaſſion of Charitie; we aboue by the hope of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Had we Chriſtians yet reaſon to doubt with Salomon, <hi>vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God did dvvell amongst men,</hi> we might alſo fall into that deficiencie of Truth, that he <hi>vvalkes about the Poles of Heauen, and conſiders not our things:</hi> but being aſſured by Faith, that he left heauen to take vp his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights amongſt the ſons of men, we cannot feare but he is full of goodnes for vs, through that goodnes loues
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34305:38"/>vs, and for that loues-ſake would haue vs to loue him againe, and to be confident in him. I will therfore with the holy Patriarche <hi>hope euen againſt hope;</hi> and with the good Iob, <hi>hope in him Though he should kill me:</hi> becauſe ſure I am, what euer ſenſe may ſeeme to ſuggeſt, <hi>he doth not loue and forſake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that his ſeconde motiue was, not that he conuerſed with vs onely, but euen became one <hi rend="margQuotes">of vs. What hath man to doe for whom God became man taking our humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon him? This is my whole Hope and entire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; for by this ſacred vnion, euery one of vs hath a part or portion in Ieſus
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:34305:39"/>Chriſt, to witt flesh and bloode.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTIONS and RESOL. Let vs then ſay with your <hi rend="margQuotes">holy Father, where a part of me raignes, their will I apprehend I raigne; where my flesh is glorified their I know I am glorious Though I am a ſinner, I cannot be diffident in this communion of grace; for what my ſinns prohibite, my ſubſtance exacts. He cannot forgett man which he beares a bout with him, and for our loue tooke vpon him.</hi> In him, we haue alreadie aſcended the heauens; in him we are ſett at the right hand of his heauenly father. O comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and admirable, and ineffable motiue of mans
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34305:39"/>hope, and confidence in ſo ſweete à Sauiour!</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that his third moriue of hope, was, not ſo much that he conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among vs, or was one of vs, as that he daigned to dye for our Loue. <hi>Be confident thou shalt attayne to his life,</hi> of glorie, <hi>vvho haſt his death for a pledge of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Let then the Diuell rage; the flesh reuoult; the world waxe madd againſt me. Let me heare nothing from them, but <hi>vvhere is novv thy God?</hi> as though I were quite for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken by him: yet wil I liue and dye in this confidence, that ſince he <hi>delightes to be vvith the ſonnes of man,</hi> he cannot delight to abandonne
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34305:40"/>him to the rage of his enemye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any further then he diſcouers it for his aduantage. That ſince for the loue of man, he <hi>became man,</hi> he loues no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man ſo litle as to looſe him. That finally ſince he dyed for him, while he was yet an enemye, he will not now, ſith he endeuours to be a ſeruant and a friend, leaue him a praye to his enemye. <hi>In ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſpe dormiam &amp; requieſcam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:34305:40"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XIV. MEDITAT.</hi> Hovv he behaued him ſelfe in Charitie shevving firſt that vvithout Charitie all ſerues for nothing.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that though <hi>Faith</hi> shew vs the good things, which nether eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, &amp;c. and <hi>Hope</hi> giues vs a comfortable confidence that we shall attayne vnto them; yet shall we neuer walke home indeede, vnleſſe <hi rend="margQuotes">Charitie <hi>giue vs feete.</hi> Thy Charitie is thy feete; with that thou art carried, where
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34305:41"/>ſo euer thou art carried: Thy two feete are the two pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, of the loue of God and thy neighbour. Run to God with theſe feete, draw cloſe to him: for he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe exhorts thee to run, and to that end enlightened thee with Faith, incourra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thee by Hope &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESOL. I playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee what euer Faith shewes me, and Hope aſſures me of, it is loue alone can make me happie. Without that, like the ſicke man of the paſſie, I lye vncomfortably, vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably, I aduance not at all: vnleſſe thy loue make me walke I ſtirre not. <hi>Grant me therfore to loue thee,</hi> as much as I deſire, and as much as I ought. Let me be wholy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34305:41"/>with the fire of thy Charitie, that I may loue thee with all my hart, yea with the verie marrow of my hart ſtrings; that thou maiſt alwayes, and in all places, be in my hart, in my mouth, and before my eyes, till at length I may ſee thee for euer, face to face, in thy heauenly Sion.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that without true Charitie, all our workes are of no value, ſeeme they neuer ſo ſpecious in the <hi rend="margQuotes">eye of the world. Charitie makes the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betwixt the ſons of God and the ſons of the Diuell. Let them ſigne themſelues with <hi>the ſigne of the Croſſe:</hi> Let them all anſwere, <hi>Amen:</hi> Let them all ſinge Alle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>luya.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34305:42"/>Let them all <hi>be baptiſed.</hi> Let them all enter into the Church; <hi>and build</hi> vp the walls of the Church; by Charitie onely are the ſons of God diſcerned from the ſons of the Diuell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Let vs not deceaue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues with the faire out-ſides of things. All that is without loue, is without life. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we beleeue, or we hope, what the Catholike Church beleeueth and hopeth; and liue within the walls of the ſame Church, and with ioy ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to all that is ſaid to it. Whether we watch, or faſt, or preach or pray, it will not all auayle vs to eternall life, vnleſſe all be both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and ordered by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34305:42"/>Without this <hi>one neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie thing</hi> all the reſt are loſt. <hi>Diligam te Domine fortitudo mea, &amp; refugium meum, &amp; liberator meus, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that as hauing <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the <hi>ſpecious vvorkes imaginable,</hi> without Charitie wee haue nothing: ſo hauing Charitie, we want nothing. <q>Where Charitie is what can be wanting, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> and where it is not, what can profit vs? The Diuell beleeues, and yet loues not: but none loues but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues. One who loues not, may, though without effect, hope for pardon: but none that loues can deſpaire. where loue is therefor, Faith and Hope alſo neceſſarily
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34305:43"/>are. Let vs then keepe this precept of our Lord, and let vs but loue one another, and we shall not fayle to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what euer he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands beſids. For in this we haue what euer other thing there is.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESOL. O God how true it was that Salomon ſaid, when he profeſſed, that together with wiſdome all good things came vnto him: for what is wiſdome, but a ſauourie knowledge, a true relish of heauenly things, which is noe other thing then Charitie? This makes vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue as we ought, hope as we ought, worke as we ought. This is one and all; vpon the purchace of which if a man imploye all his ſubſtance, he
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34305:43"/>shall repute it all, as nothing at all. Vpon this then will I ſettle my whole intentions vpon this ſpend all my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and thoughts, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>THE XV. MEDITAT. <hi>VVHAT CHARITIE IS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider what Charitie is, and you will receaue from Saint Auguſtine, that <q>it is a loue of the cheife Good! <hi>or,</hi> Charitie is a vertue wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we deſire to ſee God, and to inioye him. <hi>Or yet more fully,</hi> Charitie is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule to inioye God for his owne ſake, and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34305:44"/>ones ſelfe and his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for God.</q> So that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is a loue which lookes onely vpon God, or for God.</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Good God how ſublime and noble an obiect! How worthy of a mans whole thoughts! Nay rather how farre is it aboue man, and who did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden him to take ſo high a flight? Ah! It was euen the ſame ſouueraigne Good which would haue it ſo. <hi rend="margQuotes">O Lord, what art thou to me, or what am I to thee, that thou shouldſt commande me to loue thee? Yea and be angrie, and threaten to lay huge punishments vpon me if I loue the not? Ah! is it not of it ſelfe a great, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34305:44"/>euen the worſt of miſeries, if I loue thee not?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that as Faith and Hope are not fruites of this baſe ſoyle, ſo nor Charitie as by our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours, and ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces we are not able to purchace them, ſo nor this; <hi>but it is ſent dovvne from heauen as the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Gods gifts,</hi> ſaith he, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Charitie is diffuſed in our harts by the holy Ghoſt vvhich is giuen to vs.</hi>) To wayne our harts from earth, and carrie them vp to heauen with her.</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O diuine and heauenly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie! Thy extraction is from Heauen; thy whole ayme or obiect is Heauen; thy whole imployment in earth is to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34305:45"/>rayſe our harts to Heauen; and, of earthly which we are, to make vs become hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly. O my ſoule let vs not loue our ſelues ſo litle, as not to imploy our ſelues wholy vpon this ſacred loue. <hi rend="margQuotes">O loue which alwayes bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and art neuer extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished, ô Charitie which art my God, let me be wholy burnt with thy fire, that I may loue thee with all my hart, with all my ſoule, with all my ſtrength; with all my aymes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that though holy charitie, be a fruite originally of Paradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, yet being planted in our harts, by the ſinger of the holy Ghoſt, we are to husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34305:45"/>water, and increaſe it. <q>For, ſaith S. Auguſt. is Charitie intirely perfect as ſoone as it is produced? No, but it is produced that it may be perfected. To witt, being produced it is nourished, by nourishment ſtrengthened, by ſtrength perfected.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFF. and RESOL. O let vs carefully watch this holy fire, that wee may neuer be ſo vnhappie as haue it dye out for want of the oyle of our workes: let all our thoughts be imployed vpon the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie of this feede of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: let it be watered with the plentifull teares of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble hart. Deare God ſmite my hart with the dart of thy loue, that my ſoule may ſay to thee, I am
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34305:46"/>wounded with thy charitie, and out of that Loue-ſore, a floode of teares may ſtreame day and night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XVI. MEDITAT.</hi> Hovv Charitie is increaſed.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider how admirable Charities commerce is, which quite contrarie to wordly riches, increaſeth by being imparted, and beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon our neighbours. Beſtowe your charitie boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully and it increaſeth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly communicate not this ſacred fire to your neighbour, and it decreaſes; languisheth,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34305:46"/>and dyeth out. <q>Money, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> and Charitie are not beſtowed alike: that by being beſtowed is diminis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed; this, is increaſed. Yea more, it increaſeth in his hands who renders it, and by how much more amply he repays it, by ſo much more plentifully he retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it. It increaſeth in his hands.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O bleſſed tradinge! eaſie, and wishfull and gaynefull traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fike! By giuing away apace, we ſpeedily waxe rich. By en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring to make others happie, we fayle not our ſelues to become happie indeed. We will therfor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the bowells of charitie, and ſtriue to doe good to all.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34305:47"/>One we will helpe with counſell, another with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; or what other wayes we may be able to aſſiſte him in.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider how exceeding eaſie, our good God hath made the increaſe of charitie: It is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that we haue ether a great power, a great purſe, or vſe any great induſtrie. For is there any thing more comon, or more within euerie mans power then a cupp of cold water? giue that onely for Gods ſake, and charitie is increaſed, and a reward is promiſed. <hi>Who,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is able to bring any excuſe, ſith God promiſeth a revvard, euen for a cupp of cold vvater.</hi> And againe, <hi>ſuch is the nature of holy loue and true charitie,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34305:47"/>that by imparting it increaſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O God how good thou art, who, while we haue nothing but by thy free gift, enables vs by the good vſe of what thou haſt formely giuen, to increaſe holy loue, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by draw a number of new bliſſings vpon vs. Ther is nothing leſſe then a cupp of cold water, nothing greater then loue; and yet euen by that, this is increaſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your holy father, that it is not onely by your purſe, power, or by the gift of a cupp of cold water, that charitie is increaſed, but euen by a good looke, a good wishe, a myld anſwere. <hi rend="margQuotes">Deſpiſe no ſuppliant, if
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34305:48"/>thou beeſt able to giue, giue. If not, shew thy affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie. God crownes our good wishes, where he finds no wealth. Let none ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay, I had not wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, charitie comes not out of our coffers onely. He who hath a hart full of charitie, neuer wants what to giue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O deare God how exceeding eaſie thou haſt made this Queene of vertues, which is indeed alone better then all the reſt together! Let vs neuer be ſo wanting to our ſelues, as to ſend any away without an Almes, ſince a good word, a looke, a wishe is able to doe it, and by ſo doing our loue is increaſed,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34305:48"/>and our title to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen inlarged.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XVII. MED<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>TAT.</hi> THE EXCELLENCIES of Charitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider with him, that <hi>there is nothing better, more pretious, more profitable, more lightſome, more ſtronge, more ſecure then charitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. What is it we looke for? or whether is it, that with paynes we run to ſeeke it? Nothing can poſſibly be found better then the beſt, nor more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, then what is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34305:49"/>&amp;c. and all that, we may poſſeſſe in charitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Nothing can better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten our blindnes, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our weaknes, or ſecure vs againſt the manifold dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of this malignant world.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that Charitie poſſeſſeth vs of the preſence and ſight of God, ſo that we need not run out into the ſtreetes to looke whom our hart loueth, <hi rend="margQuotes">ſince the eyes of Faith diſcouers alreadie in our owne hart whom we loue. Why doe we ſend him who hath cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie a farr of to ſee God. Let him obſerue his owne conſcience, and there he ſees God: for if Charitie inhabites there, there alſo inhabits God. Would we
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34305:49"/>happily ſee him in heauen? Lets haue charitie, and he is in our hart as in Heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O the bliſſe, and glorie, and Maieſtie of a louing hart! O humane hart, not ſo much now a hart, as a Heauen or Paradice, ſince thou art made a Manſion for the God of glorie. Doe not, doe not my hart gadd abrode, and by a degenerous conuerſation for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett with whoſe preſence thou art honored, thou haſt by loue gott <hi>Deus tuus &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi> Contemne for his loue all other thinges ſaying. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus meus mihi &amp; ego illi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider, <hi rend="margQuotes">whether a greater commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations could be putt vpon Charitie then by ſaying God
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34305:50"/>is Charitie. A short prayſe, and yet a great prayſe. Short in ſpeech, great in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Yes, it is quickly ſaid, God is charitie; but good God; whether are our thoughtes carried by that word? <hi>God is Charitie?</hi> By poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing Charitie then wee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe God, but God is all good things, therfore by poſſeſſing Charitie, we poſſeſſe all that good is in Heauen and in Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O short and great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation indeed. ſith ſo great, as nothing can be added. Since greater or better then God nothing can be imagined by men or Angells. Nor is it a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane perſuaſion we haue for it, but an aſſurance of faith,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34305:50"/>that <hi>God is Charitie, and vvho remaynes in Charitie remaynes in God, and God in him.</hi> O my ſoule what an honor and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is this amidſt all the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and afflictions of the world, that by loue thou art able to become Gods Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and he thyne! And if thy beloued be thyne! and thou his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what can be wanting to a well borne hart?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XVIII. MEDITAT.</hi> A continuation of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Charitie.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="margQuotes">COnſider that Charitie alone is not vexed at
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34305:51"/>anothers felicitie, becauſe she knowes no emulation. She alone is not tranſported with her owne felicitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe she ſwells not with pride. She onely is not ſtung with a bad conſcience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe she wrongs no body, Amidſt contumelies she is ſecure: amongſt hatreds friendly: amongſt braules pleaſant: amidſt deceipts, innocent: lamenting at iniquities, and reſuming hart vpon the diſcouerie of Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLVT. Who is then ſo happie as one inioying Charitie? What hath the world which can giue ſo ſolide and ſure a content? Yea what hath it that is not brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me full of diſcontent? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34305:51"/>the charitable man meets with no vexation, no emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no ſwelling; but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, ioy, peace, patience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the shelter of a good conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, are that happie mans share. O diuine Charitie how thou filleſt the harts which thou doſt poſſeſſe, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, ſweetnes and tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie! Ah! they ſeeme euen to enter into the ioy of their Lord.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that <hi rend="margQuotes">it is Charitie which makes all the good Angells, and all Gods ſeruants compagnions in the bonde of ſanctitie, and it ioynes vs and them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amongſt our ſelues, and ſubiects vs to him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. See how it leagues heauen
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34305:52"/>and earth together, and putts vs in mynd what title we haue to it, makes Angells and men fellow ſeruants, and euen in a manner equall in honor, and chaynes them together in lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of holy loue, which is true ſanctitie, ô wishfull and deare bonds! See what a ſweete or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it eſtablisheth betwixt man and man making each one loue and honor, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to an other, without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting their due ſubiection to God, to whom incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aboue all, loue honor and glorie is due.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider <hi>vvhat a huge great good, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is, vvhich vvithout our labour, makes vvhat is good in others our ovvne.</hi> Hence it was that the Pſalmiſt holily glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34305:52"/>that he is made partaker of all that loue God, and keepe his commandements.</p>
                  <p>AFFEDTION and RESOLV. Ah my ſoule if thou haſt but charitie, alls thyne owne. There is no good worke done in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or in earth but thou haſt a share of it. Heauen and earth makes but one great Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> comon wealth, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Charitie is the Queene, and lodgeth in thy hart What euer prayers, faſtings, auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, almes-deeds ſufferances are exerciſed within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſe of the Catholike Church are partly thyne, while thou art rooted in Charitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:34305:53"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XIX. MEDITAT.</hi> OF SOME MOTIVES of the loue of God.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins firſt motiue of the loue of God was that he firſt <hi rend="margQuotes">loued him. The loue wherby God loues vs cannot be comprehended nor chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for he loued vs not onely ſince the tyme we were reconciled to him by the blood of his ſon, but he euen loued vs before the world was made, that we together with his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſon, might be his
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34305:53"/>ſons, before we were yet any thing at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECT. and RESOLVT. While I yet was not, and ſo was nothing, my infinitly good God had thoughts of goodnes for me, to rayſe me out of that abiſſe of nothing; and make me that ſomething which now I am; being made, he fell in loue with his owne worke, meerely out of the abundance of his owne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, without any neede he had of it at all; and made vs ſons, ſons and heirs of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kingdome we had no title too. Ah my ſoule, if we will not begin to loue, at leaſt being thus graciouſly preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, let vs not ſticke to pay loue for loue. The hart is too hard, which, (though it will
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34305:54"/>not freely giue) will not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leaſt render what it owes!</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that his ſecond motiue was, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue greatnes of Gods loue to vs, ſuch as we were, which <hi rend="margQuotes">went ſo farre that he ſpared not his owne onely ſon, but deliuered him to death, and the death of the Croſſe for all of vs, vs, who where wicked ſinners. Remember how much he loued, that we may not deſpaire; whom, or what kind of creatures he loued, that we waxe not proude.</hi> A ſon for a ſeruant, an that a moſt wicked one: deliuered vp to death, and that à moſt ignominious one</p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. O God I cannot looke vpon that great price, that infinitly
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34305:54"/>great price, the pretious blood of a ſon ſpent for the redemption of a ſeruant; but of a ſon, who was a firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, an onely begotten, and an onely beloued one, one to thyne owne hart, in whom thou wert intirely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, one, in a word, in euery thing equall to thy ſelfe. I cannot, I ſay, looke vpon it, but with much loue and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence: Nor can I reflect vpon the ſeruant, the poore miſerable and ſinfull ſeruant vpon which it was ſpent, but with much confuſion. O God what is man that thou shouldſt ſo putt thy hart vpon him: but ô man what is God to thee? And yet thy hart departs ſo eaſily from him?</p>
                  <p n="3">III. POINT. Conſider that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34305:55"/>his third motiue was not tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he loued vs firſt, and moſt, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prepared no other reward for our loue then himſelfe <q>What then, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> our worshipe of God haue noe reward? Ah yes, but noe other then the verie God himſelfe whom we worshipe Seeke nothing of him, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout him, he himſelfe wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuffice thee.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Ah! that hart is conuinced to be intolerably greedie and vnſatiable, whom God ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth not: At leaſt Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> noble hart finds all plentie, meere want to him, which is not his verie God: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he petitions for nothing els. <hi>Render me thy ſelfe? giue me thy ſelfe: for thee I vvish,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34305:55"/>thee I ſeeke, thee I hope for; to thee hath my hart ſaid, I haue ſought thy countenance ô Lord!</hi> And therfore, what euer my Lord God is diſpoſed to beſtowe on me, let him take it all away, and let him giue me himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE XX. MEDITAT.</hi> In vvhat manner and meaſure God is to be loued.</head>
                  <p n="1">I. POINT.</p>
                  <p>COnſider that the beſt, manner of louing God, is to loue him chaſtly, that is, with puritie of intention; with as litle of our owne reſpects and intereſt as may be, but
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34305:56"/>becauſe he is God, that is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitlie good, or infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi rend="margQuotes">Let vs loue him ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that we loue no other thing beſides himſelfe. I, that we may be made worthy of his heauenly imbracemets let vs diſcharge our ſelues of the care of all earthly things, and lets adheare to him alone gratis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Too litle he loues thee, ô Lord, who loues any thing, beſids thee, yea euen with thee, which he loues not for thee: for alas the innocent lambe who was ſlaughtered for vs, is worthy to receaue glorie, and honor, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: not that, in reſpect of his good gifts onely, but euen becauſe in himſelfe, he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34305:56"/>is infinitly wiſe, infinitly powerfull, infinitly beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, infinitly good, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in him ſelfe, in a moſt eminent manner; all the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects of good by which a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man can be drawen to loue. Let vs loue him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs loue him euen for his ſelfe ſake, and for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, as farre as we are able.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. POINT. Conſider that the beſt meaſure of louing God, is, to imitate his loue to vs, and loue him without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: for ſith the obiect of our loue is infinite, should not our loue alſo, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, be infinite? <hi>Thou art im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe, ô Lord, and vvithout meaſure ought thou to be loued and prayſed by thoſe vvhom
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34305:57"/>thou haſt redeemed vvith thyne ovvne pretious blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Come lets loue him, lets loue him, he deſerues all loue, yea more then all; for he hath loued vs to make vs, he hath loued vs being made: he hath loued vs firſt and moſt: he loued vs ſo farre as to giue his ſon, and to be readie to giue himſelfe, if we loue againe. Ah! let vs blush and be as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, if after all this, we find our ſelues ſlowe to loue.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:34305:57"/>
                  <p>MEDITATIONS FOR SEAVEN DAYES.</p>
                  <p>TO BE VSED BY THE Canoneſſes Regulars of the Order of Sainte Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, in the Monaſterie of SION.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Eſtablished at Paris.</p>
                     <bibl>A. <hi>1634.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>As well before their clothings and Profeſſions os otherwiſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>I vvill leade her into the vvilderneſſe: and I vvill ſpeake to her harte.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Oſee 2.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>AT PARIS, By GABRIEL TARGA,</p>
                  <p>M. DC. LXV.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb facs="tcp:34305:58"/>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34305:58"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITATION FOR THE FIRST DAY. The preparatorie prayer shall be the <hi>Hymne Veni Creator,</hi> with the prayer <hi>Deus quicorda.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE FIRST POINTE.</hi> Of Gods Benefits to man in his Creation.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONISDER that God who is infinitly gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, and infinitly, and evernally happy in himſelfe, ſeeinge thinges
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:34305:59"/>which are not, as thinges that are, out of his meere Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without any neede of vs, beinge neither preuented by any merits of ours, not prouoked by hopes of retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, rayſed vs out of nothinge to his owne likeneſſe; preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs with the whole world; made vs abſolute Lords ouer it, and ouer all the great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of thinges compriſed in it, for our vſe. Finally he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed vs with a reaſonable ſoule; capable of himſelfe, to enioy him for euer.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. Where were wee, where were wee (ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe, or ſoe longe agoe) my ſoule? where were wee, and all that wee glory in, while wee yet were not? Ah while wee slept in our nothinge, he
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34305:59"/>who watches ouer Iſraël slept not. <hi>But loued vs vvith a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall loue.</hi> he made a world for vs; not vs for the world: he made vs Lords ouer it, not ſlaues to it. He gaue vs all thinges to vſe, not to inioy: to ſolace our pilgrimage, not to ſtay vs from our contry. Heauen, my ſoule, is our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: the Kinge of Heauen our poſſeſſion, which we are made to inioy. Be it farre from vs to loue the benefits, more then the bountiful be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor: or to glory in our ſelues; or any thinge; while we and they are Equally his free gifts:</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="118" facs="tcp:34305:60"/>
                        <head>THE SECONDE POINTE. <hi>Of mans regeneration.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Conſider that though the benefit of creation be great, yet that of regeneration farre exceeds it, whereby we are borne to a new and better life; life euerlaſtinge. By that, we were made, and called men: by this, wee were made, and called by Chriſt his owne name, Chriſtians, or men of Chriſt. By that, he gaue vs power to liue and raigne ouer all the creatures: by this, to be little leſſe then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells, yea to be like to our creator in iuſtice, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. We were borne dead, but by pure grace, we were reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:34305:60"/>in baptiſme, made do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtikes of his houſe the Catholike Church, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by confirmation, fedd and fatned by his holy word, and euen his owne pretious body and bloud. Whereby wee are not onely called his ſeruants, but are indeede his freinds, nor his freinds onely, but his ſonns, nor his ſonns alone but his ſpouſes.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. If all, my ſoule, that we are, be due to God for our creation, by which we are all, that wee either are, or haue in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature, what will be due for our better beeinge by our regeneration, which makes vs citizens of the Saintes, and Gods owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtikes, his friends his ſonns,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:34305:61"/>his ſpouſes? O what hart is able to conceaue the highth of the dignity, to be made, by grace, of ſonns of the earth, the ſonns of God: of diſloyall ſubiects, he ſpouſes of Chriſt? and yet, my ſoule, ſuch wee are which was not granted to all; ſuch wee are by his free goodneſſe, and mercy. If therefore, all that wee haue in the order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or grace, we had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly, from his free gift, let all be employed, and hartily referred, to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:34305:61"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE SAME DAY. <hi>Of the obligations vvhich vve contract in Baptiſme.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of regeneration in Baptiſme is a benefite of preference, and of ſingular excellencie, ſince of ſlaues of the Diuell, it renders vs chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deren of God, and reintitles vs to our right in the Kingdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of Heauen: ſo it bringes with it greate obligations to which we are all indiſpenſably ſubiect. We ſolemnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſed therin, in the face of the Church. Firſt to renounce
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:34305:62"/>the diuell and all his pompes, wiles, and allurementes (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he endeuours inceſſantly to worke our eternall ruine.) That is, to deteſt and flye the concupiſcence of the flesh; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence of the eyes: and pride of life which are the Diuells baites, wher-in he inſnares the whole world, and inſlaues it to his accurſed do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</p>
                        <p>Theſe renounciations, ô my ſoule, are the promeſſes we ſolemnely made in our Baptiſme. Theſe are the chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian duties to which we are all abſolutly oblidged; be we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſons, or be we ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: according to theſe we shall be iudged at the laſt day. It highly behoues vs then, to run ouer our life paſt in the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:34305:62"/>bitterneſſe of our harts, and obſerue whether our holy profeſſions haue bene ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by anſwerable practiſes: and whether due performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces followed our ſolemne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. Haue we indeede, my ſoule, renounced the Diuell and all his pompes? Or rather, haue we not left Chriſt, and followed his wicked allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Vpon what follies haue we not feaſted our eyes? To what highth hath not our thoughtes aſpired? Of what impurities, and diſloyalties, haue not our hartes, at leaſt, bene brimme full. <hi>Obſerue and lament our miſeries.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="124" facs="tcp:34305:63"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Of the ſeconde obligation vvhich vve contracte in Baptiſme.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that the ſeconde obligation which we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracte in Baptiſme, is, to be liſted among the ſoldiers of Ieſus Chriſt, to fight vnder the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Croſſe, and openly to profeſſe his lawe. That Sweete lawe of loue which conteynes all Chriſtian dutie: the loue of God incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aboue all other thinges, as being infinitly louelie, and compriſinge in himſelfe all the motiues and obligations of loue: and the loue of our neighbour as our ſelues; that is, in order to God, in God, and for God. All the loue we can afford to the reſt of the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:34305:63"/>creatures, is but onely for ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces to our neceſſities and pouerties: as prouiſions for the way of our pilgrimage: to be vſed, not to be inioyed, not to haue our hates fixed vpon, which are wholie due to God and our neighbour.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Ah, my ſoule, had we bene to haue made choyce of what lawe we our ſelues had moſt deſired (not to haue receiued it from the hand of our al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie maker, who had full power to impoſe what lawe he pleaſed vpon the workes of his hands) what other lawe would we haue wished, but that which we haue? A lawe by which we are not permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely, but euen comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to loue our Kinge, the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:34305:64"/>Kinge of Kinges the Kinge of glorie. What more hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? To loue him wholy, from whoſe loue and bountie we haue all that we haue. What more reaſonable? To loue him from whoſe libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie we expect all that we yet want; the poſſeſſion of his heauenly Kingdome; the inioyment of himſelfe for all eternitie. What more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? And as to the other parte of the lawe, what poore liues should we not leade; nay what deathes, and Hells should we not ſuffer, did we in lieu of loue to our neighbour, afford him onely neglect, ſcorne, and hatred. Let me loue thee then, ô my deare Lord, and my neighbour in thee, and for thee, for euer.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="127" facs="tcp:34305:64"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE SECONDE DAY. Of the third obligation contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Baptiſme.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that the third obligation that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted in Baptiſme, was, that we are bound to liue the life of Chriſt: according to that of S. Paule: <hi>I liue, not novv I, but Ieſus Chriſt liues in me: for vve are buried togeither vvith him by Baptiſme:</hi> and ought alſo to ryſe with him, and walke after him, in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life: becauſe he left vs an example, and his will is, that we should followe his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:34305:65"/>fooſtepps: that is that we should walke in the lowlie pathes of humilitie, pouertie, and abiection, as he did from his verie firſt ſteppe into this world in labours, hunger and thirſt from his youth: in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering reproches, contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and outragious conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pts, all his life longe: in being abandonned at his death by his Apoſtles, and euen by his heauenly Father: <hi>my God, my God, vvhy haste thou forſaken me?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. The life of Chriſt, my ſoule, is our paterne; the imitation of it, is our obligation; and the liuely expreſſion of it is our perfection. Let vs ſeeke noe other, nor other way, then by humbly following his
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:34305:65"/>footeſtepps. To that he calls, vs: <hi>learne of me vvho am mylde and humble in harte:</hi> not to high ſpeculations, with are more apt to fill vs with vanitie, then feede vs with ſolide foode. Caluarie was left vs for the imitation of his vertues, Thabor onely to admire his Maieſtie: He is our <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> our begining and our end. Let all our applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be to him, and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences of him. Let all our conuerſations be with him; our deſires followe him; our diſcourſes of him; our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall cryes to him. O my deareſt Lord and ſauiour, thou, my loue; thou, my life. Let this couenant be made betwixt vs. Let me wholy dye to my ſelfe, that thou
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:34305:66"/>alone mayſt liue in me: Let my paſſions be wholy ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; that thou alone mayſt be heard in me. Let all my ſollicitous cares, which are fruitleſſe without thee, wholy ceaſe, that thou onely mayſt worke in me.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all thoſe former bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, and obligatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contracted therby, we haue bene ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratfull, and neglectfull of our owne good, as litle to mynde them. Nay like true Prodigalls we haue diſſipated and ſpent, all thoſe gracious, and Godlike talents, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting our promeſſes and obligations, we haue returned backe into the ſlauerie of the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:34305:66"/>Diuell. And here it was in dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that our good God magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his mercyes towards vs. We run from him into a fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne land, and he leaues the ninetie nine to ſeeke vs. Wee ſtrike at him by ſinne, and euen crucify him againe, and he ſupportes vs with patience. We ſteppe downe to hell, and he brings vs backe. He frequently knockes at our harts, by his holy word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to our eares; by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall voyce inculcated to our hartes; by wholſome tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations multiplyed vppon vs, and breakes through our deafneſſ. And hauinge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wrought all this in vs, he crownes his owne mercyes by takeinge vs againe into his familiarity? and he, and all
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:34305:67"/>his courte reioyceth at our conuerſion.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O thou God of mercy! to what a length haſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended thy patience with me? It was I, that ran from thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Land of diſproportion I, that forſooke thee, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of liueinge water, and made to my ſelfe ciſternes, broken ciſterns which could hold noe water. I, that turned the vſe of thyne owne giftes to abuſe, by loueinge them more then thy ſelfe (in ſuch or ſuch an occaſion) I that ſtept downe into Hell (at ſuch or ſuch a time; ſoe, or ſoe often) and thou the while ceaſedſt not to redouble thy cryes: <hi>Why vvilt thou perish ô thou houſe of I ſraëll; Why doſt thou
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:34305:67"/>loue vanity, and ſeeke a lye? looſe thy chaynes from thy necke ô thou captiue daughter of Sion.</hi> At leaſt after all thy diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, <hi>call mee but Father.</hi> Ah, my ſoule, be noe longer deafe to all theſe gracious inuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but run, though alas but too late, to that Father of mercyes, and ſay, with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humbled hart: <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I haue offended againſt heauen, &amp; againſt thee, &amp; I am noe longer vvorthy to be called thy Sonne:</hi> deale with mee onely as with one of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relings of thy houſe.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:34305:68"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE SECONDE DAY. The greeuouſneſſe of ſinne.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider what ſinne is, and your holy father S. Auguſtine will teache you that it is noe ſubſtance at all, but a miſerable and accurſed <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Yet ſuch a nothinge it is, that man becomes nothing therby <hi>(nihil fiuntbomines cum peccant)</hi> yea worſe then no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſince it is the verie death of the ſoule <hi>(peccatum mors eſt animae.)</hi> Or take it from him with the whole Catholike Church, in more ample and expreſſiue tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. <hi>Sinne is a vvord a thought,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:34305:68"/>a deede againſt the eternall lavv,</hi> or prime reaſon, which is God himſelfe. What doe we then, when we ſinne, but ſpeake, thinke or doe, againſt Gods eternall Lawe, or God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Ah my ſoule, my ſoule, it is too hard for thee to kicke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the pricke; which by how much more we aſſault it, by ſo much more we are woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by it. It is againſt God himſelfe that ſinne ryſeth vp; againſt that great, dreadfull all-mightie, reuengfull God, whom were it in its power, it would deſtroye: ſince the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as ſuch, would neither haue God wiſe to know, nor iuſt and powerfull to punish his iniquitie. Alas, what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34305:69"/>can wormes, and piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires expect by wraſling with Elephants? Our ſtrength is like to a ſpiders webbe; how dare we then ſtrugle with om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie whoſe will none reſiſtes? In wraſling we shall onely meete with our owne ruine. <hi>In diſputing neuer find repoſe, nor be able to anſvver one for a thouſand:</hi> for, to conclude with S. Paule, <hi>ô man vvho art thou that doſt anſvver God?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Of the lamentable effects of ſinne.</head>
                        <p>Conſider what grieuous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages the poore ſoule recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues by mortall Sinne. It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priues of grace &amp; ban<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>isheth the holy ghoſt out of the hart
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:34305:69"/>which it did inhabite. It brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes the league of freindshippe which was betwixt God &amp; vs, &amp; leaues vs his enemyes, and ſlaues of the Diuell, his &amp; our worſt enemie: It robbs vs of the right we had to poſſeſſe God for euer, leaueinge only Hell for our inheritance. It wounds, makes hideous, &amp; euen Kills that otherwiſe im<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ortall ſoule of ours: in a word, it makes vs crucify Ieſus Chriſt againe, &amp; in effect tread the ſacred bloud of Ieſus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feete.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. Oh accurſed fruites of Sinne! O ſaith God himſelfe by the mouth of Ieremie, Know &amp; ſee how euill &amp; bitter a thinge it is for thee to haue left the Lord thy God. Ah my ſoule,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:34305:70"/>theſe are not dreames imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, or rethoricall ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, but euen Chriſtian truthes which none dare deny, how doe we then dare to dally with danger, to ſeeke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, to drinke downe ſinne like water? If therefore the world, the flesh, or the Diuell tell of I Know not what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightes, let vs haue this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſe replye ſtill before our eyes, but they are too dearely bought, with the loſſe of the holy ghoſt and all his giftes, Gods friendshippe, and his eternall inheritance, &amp; become the obiecte of his hate. This moment of falſe libertie is not worth beinge aſlaue to the Diuell for euer. This honnor lookes fawning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vppon mee: but it were
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:34305:70"/>madneſſe to purchaſe it with eternall diſgrace. This gold glitters agreeably, yet it is not worth the hauing: ſince it will ſerue onely to buy Hell.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE THIRD DAY. Sinne is deteſtable to God.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider in what horror and deteſtation wee should haue it, ſince wiſdome it ſelfe doth ſoe abhorre &amp; deteſt it. The Almighty eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, whoſe goodneſſe cannot be queſtioned without impiety; nor his iuſtice be impeched without blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; nor his mercy be exacted
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:34305:71"/>without preſumption: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge indeede, not ſoe much good as euen effentially goodneſſe it ſelfe, nor ſoe much iuſt as iuſtice it ſelfe, nor ſoe much mercifull as mercy it ſelfe; for one ſinne of pride throwes downe the third parte of the Angells in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell, irrecouerably, without any further hope of mercy.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. If, my ſoule, this be not leſſe a truth, which all the Chriſtian world willingly imbraces, then the former; how comes it to paſſe that mans follie dare be ſoe damnably aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as to fall in loue with Sinne, which wiſdome ſoe highly deteſts? How, how, I ſay, dare we liue in league with it, &amp; be willinge to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:34305:71"/>meete with it at euery turne? If it haue made Angells Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, what priuiledge haue men not to dreade the like effects? not for one or a few, but euen for thouſands of ſinnes; (euery man makeinge reflection in himſelfe of the multitude of his ſinnes) downe then, my ſoule, downe; place thy mouth in the duſt, and whilſt thou canſt not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate the rigour of Gods iuſtice to the Angells, turne thy ſelfe more earneſtly to admire his inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to thee, humbly confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge, that otherwiſe Hell had beene longe ſince thy habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: makeinge a firme reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſinge his mercyes eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="142" facs="tcp:34305:72"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINT.</hi> Adam by ſinne turned out of Paradiſe.</head>
                        <p>Conſider how the ſame God who is equally goodneſſe, mercy and iuſtice, for one acte of diſobedience, throwes Adam out of the happie ſtate wherin he had placed him, and ſubiects him and all his poſteritie, to multitudes of miſeries of body and mynde (ſuch as we all daylie expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience) to heate, cold, cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, innumerable ſorts of ſickneſſes, and euen to death it ſelfe; and that too, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the death of his body, but euen to a ſecond death, the death of the ſoule: ſo that there was not any ſaluation left for all the ſonns of men,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:34305:72"/>at any leſſe rate then the death and bloud, of a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Ieſus-Chriſt.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O my ſoule, if this truth be taught vs by faith; if we feele it by a ſadd and vniuerſall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; if it be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to vs by the death of a God: let it printe in our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, an abſolute horrour, and deteſtation of ſinne, which is ſo horrible, and deteſtable in the ſight of God; and which his iuſtice punishes ſo rigou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly. And let vs noe leſſe adore that ſterne iuſtice of his, then extolle, and dearly imbrace his mylde mercy; who to expiate the ſinne of an vngracicus diſloyall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, ſacryficeth the bloud of a dearely beloued, and deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34305:73"/>louing, and wholy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, and onely child. Be that Iuſtice alwayes admired, and dreaded; and be that mercy magnified, and loued, by men.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE THIRD DAY. Sinne putt a God to death.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that our ſweete Sauiours paines (the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re price of our redemptió) are vniuerſall; noe parte of his body paſſes without its parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular punishment. His head is tormented with pullinge of the haire, with blowes with thornes; His face with foule
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:34305:73"/>ſpittings &amp; boxes. His tongue with thirſt veneger &amp; gale. His torne shoulders with the heauie loade of the Croſſe. His armes with rude extentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; rackinge. His ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; feete with cruell nayles. His whole body all ouer with ſtripes. His Sinewes with conuulſions. His arteries and veynes with wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theredneſſe. His vitall partes with an incredible effuſion of his pretious bloud: ſoe that what the prophet foretolde was fully verified: from the ſole of his foote, to the crowne of his head, there was noe ſoundneſſe. See then whether there be any ſorrow like his ſorrowe.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. Alas? it is but too euident, my deareſt Lord, thy ſorowes paſſe all our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:34305:74"/>&amp; yet my ſoule, it is maieſtie that is thus ſmitten: it's innocencie which thus ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers. It's indeede the God of Gods, whoſe immenſitie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be comprehended; whoſe perfections &amp; excellencies cannot be numbred; whoſe goodneſſe is boundleſſe, whoſe mercyes cannot be matched. Alas my deformed, hidden, crucifyed Lord? whither hath mercy, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, loue to miſerable man ledd thee? was it thought fittinge to this goodneſſe, that thy wounds should be without number, as are thy perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; mercyes to man? ſoe to make an abſolute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that as there is noe loue, ſoe are there noe ſorrowes like to thyne. Let me not liue but to loue thee, &amp;
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:34305:74"/>ſuffer for thy ſake.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider further that he ſufferd inall his ſenſes, by the preſence of all the obiects of ſorrow, He ſaw his choyſen Apoſtles ſleeping, while he was ſweating bloud. He ſaw the Trayter, whom he had newly fedd with his owne bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body &amp; bloud, come in the heade of a barbarous band to apprehend him. He ſaw the execrable crueltie of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull nation, which he had alwayes oblidged and loued by preference. Finally, his cares were full of blaſphee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſcoffes and ſcornes: and his eyes and harte of the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, teares, and bloud of a God dying.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. And yet, my
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:34305:75"/>ſoule, it is the very naturall ſonne of God that ſuffers all this? He is the ſplendour of his fathers glorie, and the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of his ſubſtance. And shall we his poore ſonns, taken in by adoption onely, ſee with drye eyes, his, full of teares and bloud? or shall we, after this ſad ſight, permitt them any more to be filled with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie? Shall our eares lye open to deſtractions, adulations, and found rumours, which hurt our ſoules, whyle his, for our ſake, are filled with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies, and blaſphemies? Shall we Chriſtians pamper the reſt of our ſenſes, with ſweetes and delicacies, while our Chriſts ſo hugely ſuffers in them all? Ah! be it euer farre from vs; to pay his loue
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:34305:75"/>with ſuch intolerable ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude!</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE III. POINT.</hi> He ſuffers in his ſoule.</head>
                        <p>But if his body vniuerſally and all his ſenſes, be ingaged in the ſufference, is his ſoule at leaſt free? Ah noe, its ſadd to death; its <hi>replenished vvith euill</hi> or ſorrow, <hi>the bitter vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of tribulations haue broken in vpon it.</hi> The horrour of death, the ingratitude of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſcorne of Nations, Pilates iniuſtice, Herods mockerie: Annas and Cayphas blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, the Scribes and Phariſies circumuentions, the Miniſters and Soldiers crueltie, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples preference of Barabbas and their tumultuous and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:34305:76"/>vniuſt <hi>Crucifige. See then vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be any ſorrovv like to his ſorrovv.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O man of dolours, and accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed to ſufferances from thy youth: Were not thy ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and, in them, thy loue to man, ſufficiently expreſſed, in abandonning that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, chaſt, and tender virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall body of thyne, to the cruell perſecutours wills, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou didſt withall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt the bitter flouds of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and deadly ſaddneſſe, enter into, and take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of thy bleſſed ſoule? Conſider: my ſoule, and ſee whether their be any ſorowe like to this ſorrow, or any loue like to his loue who gaue vp his ſoule to ſuch ſorrowes for
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:34305:76"/>thy ſake? If the horrour of death inuade thee, thy Maſter went before thee, &amp; waded through to death it ſelfe. Proue friends vngratefull? ſo they were to thy Lord. Are others, of leſſe worth prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before thee? but ſo was Barrabas before thy Maſter Chriſt. Remember, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, my ſoule, that the ſeruant is not greater then his maſter &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE IV. POINTE.</hi> He ſuffers vvithout a comforter.</head>
                        <p>Conſider his body's tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, his ſenſes offended, his ſoule afflicted and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Is none left to comfort him? Noe none, <hi>relictus eſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> he's abandoned. left all
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:34305:77"/>alone, to wraſtle with all the legions of ſorrowes. <hi>Non eſt qui conſoletur eum.</hi> There is none left to comfort him. Was there euer ſo pittious a ſpectacle? His Apoſtles are fled; Peter followes a farre of and ſweares he knowes him not. The dolorous mother ſtands neere the Croſſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but her preſence affords ſo ſmale ſolace, that her ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ſerue to redouble his. The Angells come not neere. His heauenly father aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donns him: nay yet more (Heauens ſtand amayſed at it) he is euen forſaken by himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, while he ſtopps the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his diuinitie, that it flow not vpon his humanitie, leauing it to ſuffer all alone without all comfort. <hi>See then
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:34305:77"/>vvhether there be any ſorrovv like to his ſorrovv!</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O, my ſoule, looke vpon the face of thy Chriſt. Admire his his vn wearied ſuffering loue. Hartily acknowledge that there is noe ſorrow like his ſorrow. Imprint in thy harte at what a deare rate thou waſt bought. Ah my ſoule! it was not with gold and ſiluer, and ſuch corruptible thinges: but with the ſorrowes, and teares, and bloud, and death, of a a God-man, our Sauiour Ieſus. With ſorrowes, which ſpredd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo vniuerſally ouer body, ſenſes, and ſoule: with teares, and bloud, ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and freely powred out: with death ſo ignominious, ſo deuoyd of all comfort, ſo
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:34305:78"/>abandonned, that it forced from the mouth of a moſt obedient and deareſt child: <hi>My God, my God, vvhy haſt thou forſaken me.</hi> Reſolue firmely then, that neither ſorrowes, nor bloodshed, nor abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor death it ſelfe, shall ſeparate vs from the loue of that deareſt Lord.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE FOVRTH DAY. <hi>Of Deathe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE FIRST POINTE.</hi> Nothinge more certaine then death, leſſe certaine then the tyme therof.</head>
                        <p>COnſider, and ſtriue to imprint in our harts, that
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:34305:78"/>which we all know, yet ſeeme not to know it; that which we all beleeue, and yet as it were, beleeue it not: to witt, that as there is nothinge ſoe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine as death, ſoe is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge ſoe vncertaine as the houre therof. Conſult our owne Knowledge vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe truthes, &amp; we Know, that neither Salomons witt, nor Samſons ſtrength, nor Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolons beauty were founde proofe againſt it. They were, and now are not, <hi>mortui ſunt,</hi> is certaine. Conſult the word of truth, and we shall finde that we are bound to beleeue what we otherwiſe Know. Conſult our ſelues againe vppon the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it; and we finde that we haue Knowne, many taken
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:34305:79"/>away, when they and their friends leaſt feared it; ſome by violent, ſome by naturall dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, ſome in their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, before they well knew what it was to liue: ſome in theire flourishinge ſpring, when vigourous youth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them they could not dye. Some in the decline of their age, while death threatned, and yet was not feared: ſoe certaine it is, that the houre of death is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to all; as Chriſt himſelfe makes it ſure to faith. Watch ſaith he, becauſe you neither know the day, nor the houre.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Dye then we muſt, my ſoule, thereis nothinge ſoe certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; departe we muſt out of this cottage of clay; Gods
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:34305:79"/>iuſtice hath pronounced the ſentence. <hi>Remember man that thou art duſt, &amp; in-to duſt thou shalt returne.</hi> But when muſt this ſentence be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? that is noe leſſe vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our youth may deceiue vs, as it hath done many. our manhoode or middle age, is not priuiledged: our ould age cannot laſt longe. What then muſt we doe, but with S. Auguſtine, quitt the vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and forth-with fixe vppon the certaine meanes, a good &amp; penitentiall life, to preuent the danger of that which cannot otherwiſe be auoyded by mortall man.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="158" facs="tcp:34305:80"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE SECONDE POINTE.</hi> Nothinge more certaine for the thinge, nothinge leſſe certaine, as to the manner.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that as we are moſt certaine that dye we muſt, &amp; as vncertaine when; ſoe are we noe leſſe ignorant, where, and how this irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence is to be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Shall it be in France or in England? at Paris or in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try; at home or abrode, in our cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, or in the Church or Garden? Shall it be by a violent, accidentall, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death? Shall we be found dead in our beds, as we haue ſeene ſome, &amp; heard of many? Or elſe, be wrought downe by a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and lingeringe diſeaſe in the preſence of many?
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34305:80"/>Shall we finally haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Sacraments, which we now haue with ſoe much eaſe, yea want not without blame? To all this, the wiſeſt amonge men is not able to anſwer. That dye we muſt is appointed by a reproachleſſe iuſtice; but when, but where, but how: mercy, ſaith S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, hath concealed, that we might expect, attend, &amp; prouide for it, in all times, places, &amp; occurrences.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If certainely we muſt dye, my ſoule, &amp; yet neither Know when, where, nor how; and if vppon that certaine vncertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne houre an eternity of bliſſe or woe depends, what a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is put vppon vs, (if we will not for moments looſe
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34305:81"/>eternities) to be ready in all tymes &amp; places. We Know not, my ſoule, we Know not when, where, or how death may ſurpriſe vs; onely this wee Know, that we haue yet an houre left vs to riſe out to four ſlumber, and it is now his preſent houre. Now then without further delay, will we, by Gods grace dye (to that, that, &amp; that, &amp;c.) that death findinge vs already dead, may not be able to hurt vs, but onely tranſlate vs to à life which Knowes nor feares not death.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:34305:81"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE SAME DAY.</hi> Nothing more dreadfull to the obſtinate ſinner, then death.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that as death contaynes the greateſt certaintie, and withall, the greateſt vncertaintie imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, ſo it bringes alonge with it, the greateſt dreade, and the greateſt comforte poſſible. That, to the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſinner; this, to the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble penitent. The ſinner vpon the approche of death, hath all the ſinnes of his whole life placed before his eyes, which he ſtill placed behinde his
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34305:82"/>backe; and would neither ſee them, nor ſorrowe for them; which now the vile Tempter aggrauates, and makes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their vttermoſt inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minitie. And hence the ſinner begins, before hand, to ſuffer the tormentes, which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beleeued (tho fruitleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through his obſtinacie) to be due to his crymes. And thus Knowing his guilt, and the punishment moſt iuſtly due to the ſame, he deeply ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends it a thinge full of horrour to fall into the hands of a liuing God. Thence he rages, and deſpaires, ſeeing himſelfe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the verie brinke of endleſſe perdition; and readie to be deliuered vp into the hands of his cruell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteres for all eternitie.</p>
                        <pb n="163" facs="tcp:34305:82"/>
                        <p>AFFECTION. and RESOLVT. O horrour which hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing equall to it! To appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend ones ſelfe to be vpon the verie brinke of eternall perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. O daunting dreade, incomparably ſurpaſſing all that ought to be dreaded! To be within a moment of falling into the hands of that euer-liuing Maieſtie, which is able to throw both the body and ſoule into Hell fire. What riches, honours, pleaſures, (were they neuer ſo opulent, ſuperlatiue, and proſperous, and remayned they too till that moment, in their full poſſeſſion, wheras indeede they all are vanished away like nightly dreames) were able to conteruayle ſo daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and damning a diſaſter?
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:34305:83"/>O my ſoule, thoſe accurſed wretches, shall then ſay with in themſelues; repenting, and ſighing (too late) for anguish of ſpirit. What hath pride profited vs? Or what aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage hath the vaunting of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches brought vs? Or what comfort hath the moſt proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous pleaſure of our whole life now left vs. Alas, alas none at all, but contrarilie a comfortleſſe, fruitleſſe, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe peniteri.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Nothing more confortable to the humble penitent.</head>
                        <p>Conſideration. But when the innocent and iuſt ſoule, or the poore humble penitent, perceiues death to creepe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:34305:83"/>vpon her, she lifts vp her lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge deiected heade with ioy, becauſe her redemption is euen at hand. She had vſed her beſt endeuours, mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to purge her ſinnes in the bloud of the lambe who was ſlaughtered for vs, and thence she co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiues an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble confidence to meere with mercy, and to be ioyfully ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in, to that celeſtiall mariage of his. In fine, she eyes death as the immediate obiect of her ioy; ſince it alone has power to deliuer her out of her loathed priſon of flesh; and to deliuer her vp into the deare hands, and diuine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of her deareſt ſpouſe whom she loues alone.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Sitt downe ſeriouſly, my
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:34305:84"/>ſoule, and count to what a high degree of conſolation it will then amounte, to heare thoſe heauenly inuitations of the heauenly ſpouſe ſaying: <hi>come, come, my ſpouſe thou shalt be Crovvned.</hi> Crowned, I ſay, <hi>vvith that crovvne of iuſtice vvhich is layd vp for, and by a iuſte Iudge shall be rendered, to them that loue his coming.</hi> The shewers of repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, are now blowen ouer: the sharpe winter of temptations, tribulations, vexations, and croſſes, which we willingly endured for the loue of God, are quite gone: <hi>ryſe vp my friend and come.</hi> O what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of deare delight, shall that happie ſoule inioye at that houre?</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="167" facs="tcp:34305:84"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE FIFTH DAY. <hi>Of Iudgment.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that dye wee muſt; that is, this ſoe much neglected ſoule of ours, muſt be turned out of the body, which was pampered, careſſed, &amp; too carefully looked to by vs, &amp; preſently after death, Iudgment (ſaith the great Apoſtle) we muſt all of vs be brought, and be made manifeſt before Chriſts Tribunall, that euery one beare away accordinge to his woorks. We haue left the world vnwillingly while wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:34305:85"/>the world leaues vs; the deareſt freind that euer we had will not goe alonge with our abandoned ſoule, nor euen permitt the body which they loued, to ly foure and twentie houres in the Roome with them. They that offended with vs, will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for vs, but leaue vs alas, to anſwer all alone.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Aye me vppon what is it that we fixe our hopes? is't vppon our ſelues; but alas theſe muddle walls fall, &amp; the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall inhabitant is turned our, Vppon the freinds that we haue purchaſed by ſinne, or other wiſe! but they haue left vs, our body is throwne into the earth, &amp; our poore ſoule is left alone to be iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:34305:85"/>Ah how much better were it ſaieth S. Auguſtine, <hi>to chuſe him for our freind, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all our freinds, vvho vvhen all forſake vs vvill be ſure to make good his truſt, at the day of our death, vvho vvhen all departe from vs, vvill not leaue vs, but vvill defend vs, &amp; conduct vs by a countrie vvhere vve haue yet noe acquaintance.</hi> Thou art my Ieſu &amp; noe other, be thou therefore my choyce in tyme &amp; in eternity.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in what a dauntinge anxiety, &amp; dreadfull expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the poore ſoule muſt needs be, findinge herſelfe all alone, to be ſentenced by a Iudge who is all knowinge: all things lyinge open, &amp;
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:34305:86"/>naked before his Eyes. All powerfull, for who reſiſts his will? all holy, &amp; ſouerainly hates Sinne. <hi>Iuſtice it ſelfe</hi> which can neither be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by bribes, nor moued by prayes. And to behold,; <hi>this knovvledge; this povver; this ſanctitie; this iuſtice;</hi> armed with implacable <hi>vvroth,</hi> and inflexable <hi>Zeale</hi> againſt the ſinner!</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Alas and woe, my ſoule, whither shall we run for shel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? To his <hi>mercy?</hi> but her tyme is paſt, she leaues the place to iuſtice. To his <hi>ſanctitie?</hi> But our ſinnes are quite oppoſite to the holyneſſe of that thrice Holy. To his <hi>Iuſtice?</hi> But alas our iniquitie ſtopps our mouthes. Shall we call vpon
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:34305:86"/>the mountaines and rockes to hide vs? But his power is a hammer bruiſing the rockes in ſunder; his knowledge pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrates the mountaines; and <hi>his Zeale and furie ſpares none.</hi> Such certainly, my ſoule, and infinitly more dreadfull then we can imagine it, will that diſmale day be found. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, we are yet in a tyme of mercye, we can yet ſafely flye from Chriſt to Chriſt; from his iuſtice to his mercye; from his power to his impotencie, in his cradle &amp;c. From the zeale and wroth of Maieſtie; to the ſweetneſſe and myld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Lambe, who comes to take away the ſinnes of the world. Finally we haue yet the meanes to hide our ſelues in the holes of the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:34305:87"/>the ſaueing rocke, and to ſaue our ſelues.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE SAME DAY. <hi>Of Hell.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that as mercy &amp; iuſtice are equall in God, or euen God himſelfe; ſoe, by the law of contraryes, they will be followed with equall effects. If God out of his mercy then, haue poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the bleſſed of the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all good thinges, vnder his heauenly raigne; which is beatitude: he will throw the accurſed into the poſſeſſion of a collection of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:34305:87"/>all euill, vnder the tyranie of the Diuell, which is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Let vs therefore ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine all that we are able of horrour, of hope turned vnto diſpaire; of the loue of God, and all we euer had deare, into hatred, &amp; deteſtation: let vs add wormes, which neuer dye, weepinge, wailing, gnashinge of teeth, brimſtone, and flouds of fire, &amp; yet we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is not that which the damned ſuffer, which will indeede, bee that, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor hath entered into the hart of man.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. Ay me my ſoule, into what a vaſt ſea of miſery, diſaſter, &amp; diſpaire, doth ſinne caſt downe poore man? we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:34305:88"/>all that euer we can of terrour, of horrour, &amp; tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; of im<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ortall wormes; fire &amp; brimſtone, &amp; yet we fall short. We adde the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all euills, &amp; yet we cannot reach to it. What is it alas? what is it, that lulles vs aſleepe, &amp; makes vs ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, of things ſoe ſenſible? O that we could deſcend into Hell aliue, &amp; conſider, who amongſt vs, were able to liue in the mideſt of deuouringe flames? And yet into ſuch is the ſinner throwne by the doome of eternall Truth: <hi>Goe you accurſed into eternall fire.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider yet more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, that as the accurſed had miſuſed all that God had
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:34305:88"/>giuen them for his ſeruice, to offend him; as body, ſoule, &amp; ſenſes, ſoe shall they all meete with theire ſeuerall tortures. The body &amp; ſoule, become fewell for deuouringe flames. All the ſenſes are replenished with obiects of horrour: the eys are full of dreedfull &amp; gaſtly Ghoſts: the ears of howlinges, roareings, execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble maledictions, &amp; blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: the ſmell of the ſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge odours iſſuinge from the bodyes of the damned: the taſte is glutted with what can be imagined moſt bitter, &amp; abbominably loathſome. Finaly, the ſenſe of touchinge meets with nothinge but flouds of tormentinge flames.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. O horrour, conſternation, &amp;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:34305:89"/>deſpaire? O lamentation of lamentations, &amp; woe, woe, woe? woe to the corruptible body which waighed downe the poore ſoule? woe to the ſoule that quickened that fleshly lumpe, &amp; gaue way to its badd inclinations. Woe to the eys &amp; eares which lay open to vanities, &amp; franticke madneſſe, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed poyſon into the harte. Woe to all the reſt of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; members, which conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſeducinge of the ſoule, &amp; to bringe it, &amp; them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to lye tormented in this flame.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINT.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that if the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate of the damned be moſt vnhappie by the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall preſence of the whole
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:34305:89"/>collection of all euill: What an infinite addition is made, to it by the priuation of all good, and that for an eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? To be for an Eternitie, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from all the bleſſed, were they neuer ſoe deare vnto vs, while they liued with vs? for an eternitie to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the peereleſſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Queene of Heauen, &amp; the ſocietie of all the Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of Angells! For an eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be exiled from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious face of God, which is man &amp; Angells eſſential bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; &amp; to deteſt, curſe, &amp; blaſpheame it for euer? Neuer to haue one moment of eaſe; conſolation or reſt, or euen the leaſt hope of any for all eternitie</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL.
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:34305:90"/>O God of mercy, now turned the Lord of reuenge, what hart hath aſſurance ennough, not to endure, but euen to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde this calamitous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the damned? ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with all ſortes of torments; remoued from all hopes, or euen deſires of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: not for ſome millions of millions of yeares, but for an eternitie! O eternitie! eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie! how longe thou art! Noe number of yeares are able to expreſſe thee; the ſands of the ſea cannot equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſe thee; after all, thou ſtill remaineſt what thou art, <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi> Ah my ſoule let vs vſe a timely preuention, &amp; not make our ſelues away to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall' torments for light &amp; short delightes (ſuch or ſuch
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:34305:90"/>&amp;c.) nor yet for the auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge of, ſuch or ſuch ſmale croſſes, afflictions, or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall loſſes. Let vs couragiouſly plucke out the Eye, and cutt of the hand, which ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; hazards our eternall loſſe: &amp; conclude with holy S. Auguſtine: <hi>Let me here be burnt, let me here be cutt in peeces. ſoe that I may not perish eternally.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE SIXTH DAY. <hi>Of Heauen.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider what this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Bleſſed and
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:34305:91"/>which they are called to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe <hi>(come poſſeſſe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you)</hi> and this, at leaſt, we shall finde, that whateuer this poſſeſſion may be, it is greater then we haue any capacitie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. Let vs looke vpon all the beauties, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies that euer our eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, and they are not it. Lets make reflection of all that euer we haue heard, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, riches, pleaſures, and all of them are not it. Let vs by helpe of imagination, put all togeither that we haue either ſeene or heard; and euen adde to them millions of millions more, and yet we are not arriued at it. Noe, for S. Paule aſſures vs: <hi>that neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:34305:91"/>heard, nor hath it entred into the mynde of man, vvhat God hath prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O my moſt bountifull Lord and Maſter. Hath thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made me capable of a Kingdome, which thy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath not inabled me at preſent to comprehend! O too too happie we, could we truly vnderſtand our owne happineſſe! But ô more then moſt vnhappie we, if we permitt ſinne to robbe vs of it; or that we otherwiſe make it a way for a meſſe of potage; or the bitter Mandragores of mixt moments of painefull pleaſures: for ſuch inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable toyes (I meane) as are daylie obiects to meaneſt eyes, and fill euery eare. Nay
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:34305:92"/>euen for the greateſt thinges our hartes can conceiue, ſince in a ſmale tyme they vanish away like dreames, and leaue nothinge in our hands. Alas! were it not a ſtrange miſerie, and madneſſe, to make away ſuch inconceiuable permane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t poſſeſſions, for ſuch knowne tranſitorie toyes?</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE. <hi>What heauen is.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>Conſider, againe, what this Kingdome, or poſſeſſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs may be; and we finde it is a ſtate of life per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly accomplished with the whole collection of all good thinges. Not a paſſage, but <hi>a ſtate,</hi> a permanencie, without change, without end, without
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:34305:92"/>irkeſommeſſe. <hi>Perfectly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished:</hi> not by halues, and peecemeales. <hi>With the vvhole collection of all good thinges.</hi> Not with a few, as here below, and thoſe, good and ill; paines and pleaſures mixt togeither, but with the whole collection of all good thinges: ſo that what euer we deſire, shall be preſent: and all that we deſire not shall be abſent eternally.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. We haue Gods word for it, my ſoule, and it cannot fayle vs, that he will shew vs <hi>all good;</hi> that is, all that is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious, gaynefull, and rich, in ſteede of the tranſitorie riches of this world: all that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming, honorable, and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious; in lieu of the vaine and vadinge honours here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe:
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:34305:93"/>all that conteynes in it ſelfe any cauſe of ioy, and iubilie, and and all that is deare and delightfull (to witt, that ineffable, vnmeaſurable, eternall waight of glorie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to S. Paule) in place of thoſe short, light, deluding, and euen painefull pleaſures (as Salomon and S. Auguſtine experienced them) for which poore man looſes himſelfe. Thus, my ſoule, doth faith aſſure vs: let not then follie perſwade vs the contrarie.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="185" facs="tcp:34305:93"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE 6. DAY. <hi>Of Heauen againe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider, the kingdome prepared for vs, is Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: <hi>come ô you bleſſed:</hi> and Beatitude is noe other thinge, then to know what is beſt, and to inioy the ſame. And wheras none but God himſelfe is our <hi>ſummum bonum, or optimum, our cheife good, or our beſt:</hi> it followes, that God himſelfe, the father, ſonne, and holy Ghoſt, is our Beatitude, or the Kingdome prepared for vs: accordinge to that: <hi>I my ſelfe vvill be thy exceeding greate
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:34305:94"/>revvarde.</hi> Him we shall ſee face to face, and in that ſight our vnderſtanding meets with all <hi>truth:</hi> him we shall ſee, and in ſeeing him, our will meetes with all <hi>good.</hi> Hence the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding hauing noe more to ſeeke, and the will noe more to loue, they fall, as it were, into a bleſſed neceſſitie, of truly ſeeing what they loue, and louing what they ſee for all eternitie.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Forgett not then, ô man, thy dignitie! By Gods mercy, and the merits of Chriſt, thou art made the ſonne of God, coheire with Chriſt, to share in his heauenly inheritance, to poſſeſſe the ſame Kingdome with him: that is, to knowe the <hi>prime truth,</hi> and loue the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:34305:94"/>
                           <hi>cheife good</hi> for euer and euer. Let not then the fables, fictions and vaine lyes of the world, take vp thyne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge made to knowe ſo great and diuine a <hi>Truth:</hi> nor the vaine loue of creatures ingage thy will, made to loue ſo ſouueraigne à <hi>Good.</hi> But crye inceſſantly here belowe with holy S. Auguſtine: <hi>Let me knovv thee, ô Lord, and knovv my ſelfe; and let me loue thee as much as I deſire, and as much as I ought.</hi> Thus, my ſoule, may we in ſome meaſure, while we liue amidſt our miſeries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, before hand, to poſſeſſe our Beatitude, which conſiſts in <hi>knovving, louing,</hi> and <hi>inioying</hi> our chiefe <hi>Good,</hi> which is God himſelfe.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="188" facs="tcp:34305:95"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Hovv Heauen is to be purchaſed.</head>
                        <p>Conſider out of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that <hi>the Kingdome of heauen ſuffers violence; and the violent beare it avvay.</hi> Yes, but we muſt learne of S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe how we are to make this violence. We are to aſſault it, not with ſwords, with clubbe, or ſtone; but with myldneſſe, with good workes, with chaſtitie. Theſe are the armes which our faith makes vſe of, in that onſett. But yet to make a right vſe therof, we muſt firſt of all, make force againſt our owne flesh and bloud, that ſo gayning domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer our ſelues, we may imploye all our abilities to force Heauen, as it were, out
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:34305:95"/>of the ſtronge hands of the Almightie. We are not to hope, ſaith S. Gregorie, to come to great honours, but by great labours and paines. We muſt mortifie our members, and all the mutinous people of our hartes, our vnrulie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and badd inclinations. So did all the ſaintes of God ſcale and winne his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. So did that greate Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the Gentiles beare it away: <hi>I chaſtiſe my body and bringe it into ſeruitude.</hi> So did the ſainte of ſaintes enter into his owne Kingdome. He ſuffered and ſo entred into his owne Kingdome.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Let vs not hope, my ſoule, that we who are but younger, and adoptiue children, should
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:34305:96"/>find any other ſafe way to heauen, then that which the naturall ſonne of God, and all his ſaintes, were to paſſe: That is, through tribulations, contumelies, and contempts. <hi>If vve ſuffer vvith him vve shall raigne vvith him.</hi> Noe, noe, the pure wheate reſerued for the heauenly granaries muſt be winnowed: the gold found worthy to haue courſe in that celeſtiall Kingdome, muſt paſſe through the hoteſt fires. Sweete S. Auguſtine putts it at the loweſt rate; that euer it can be expected: and yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to him it will coſt vs noe leſſe then all we are. <hi>The Kingdome of heauen,</hi> ſaith that excellent Sainte, <hi>is vvorth as much as thou art: giue thy ſelfe and thou shalt haue it.</hi> Doe not
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:34305:96"/>ſtand barganing, my ſoule, and grudging at the price. The naturall ſonne of God, purchaced it at noe leſſe a rate for himſelfe, and thee.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE 7. DAY.</hi> A ſerious reflection to be made, as vvell of Gods gracious gifts beflovved vpon vs: as minaces pronounced againſt vs.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider (by way of a ſerious reflection of all the former Meditarions) that ſince God hath bene ſo gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to vs, and we ſo vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him, as greatly and
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:34305:97"/>frequently to haue offended his diuine Maieſtie. Since he ſo ſouuerainly hates ſinne wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>of we ſtand guiltie. Since death is ſo vncertaine: iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo dreadfull. Hell ſo intolerable; and the ioyes of Heauen prepared for vs, ſo ineffablely great; conſider, I ſay, what a neceſſitie is put vpon vs (if our hartes be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, either with dreade of vnſpeakable torments, or loue of Beatitude.) To make a good vſe of the tyme, which by Gods mercy, we yet haue, to redeeme tyme loſt: to make hay whyle the ſunne shines: and to treaſure vp the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Manna before the ſunne ſett.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Noe my ſoule, we will dare
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:34305:97"/>noe lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be ſo audaciouſly aduenterous as to triffle our pretious tyme with cold <hi>cras craſſes.</hi> But euen at this verie moment I will ſtriue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude an eternall peace with God. It is dreadfull to come too late; to heare, verily verily I know you not, and to finde the dore shurt. My conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therfor shall henceforth be in heauen, and heauenly thinges. I will deſcende into Hell aliue, to obſerue the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride torments of that gaſtly denne. I will expect death at all houres, ſince none knowes the houre indeede in which it may ſurpriſe me. I will iudge my ſelfe without flatterie, that I may not be more rigourouſly iudged. I will endeuour in earneſt and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:34305:98"/>with my whole harte to hate ſinne, which God ſo ſouerai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnely hates. And the reſidue of my life shall be ſpent, that by true and hartie pennance (the onely true refuge after ſinne) I may take reuenge of my ſelfe, according to S. Paule, for hauing offended, ſo gracious a Benefactour, and ſo dreadfull a Maieſtie.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE SECONDE POINTE.</hi> Hovv vve are to returne to God by pennance according to S. Auguſtine.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that the way to returne to God by pennance preſcribed by S. Auguſtine, is: Firſt (as to the tyme) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <hi>ſpeedily,</hi> and without all delay: becauſe he who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:34305:98"/>pardon to the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinner; promiſed noe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine tyme for him to repent in, but willed him not to delay his conuerſion. Secondly, (as to the manner) mournfully and with confuſion. Euery one ought to lament ouer himſelfe, as ouer a deade corps: and expreſſe huge grones vpon his deade ſoule. Thirdly, in qualitie of Iudge: Mounte into the Tribunall of your owne harte, proue your owne Iudge, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe iuſtice vpon your ſelfe. And in the firſt place, take your ſelfe from behind you, where you endeuoured to hide your faults, and not to be ſeene, and ſtand araigned before your ſelfe. Let feare torture you, till a true confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:34305:99"/>burſt out from an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled harte: and ſay to God: <hi>I achnovvledge myne iniquitie, and my ſinnes are continually before myne eyes.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. and RESOLVT. My ſoule, hauing thus, ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, mounefully and with the iuſtice and rigour of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall Iudge, diſcuſſed our ſelues, let vs, preſently, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and confidently haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to God for the reſt. We haue an vnhappie power in our ſelues to commit ſinne <hi>Thy perdition is from thy ſelfe, ô Iſrael:</hi> but our ſaluation is from God alone. To his mercy therfor, which is aboue all his workes, let vs betake our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, ſaying in the bitterneſſe of our harte: Grant mercy ô Lord to that miſerable
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:34305:99"/>wretch, whom thou ſo longe ſparedſt in his crymes. O im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe pietie, take compaſſion vpon a confeſſing cryminall. O publike mercy, looke vpon him with the eye of pitie who hath proued cruell againſt his owne ſoule, ah. I should apprehend my caſe, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, deſparate, did I not bewaile it in the fight of an infinite goodneſſe; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my wounds incurable, had I not recourſe to an all-ſouueraigne Phyſition. Let me perceiue the effects of thy myldneſſe, hauing ſo longe mercifully ſuſpended the sword of reuenge, and let the multitudes of my miſeries, be drunke vp in the multitudes of thy draineleſſe mercyes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="198" facs="tcp:34305:100"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE SAME DAY.</hi> Hovv vve are to returne to God by the example of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall child.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that the poore prodigall hauing conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all his ſubſtance, and ryſing (by Gods preuenting grace) out of the ſleepe of ſinne where he had longe layd, he ſaid in himſelfe: <hi>hovv many hyrelings are there in my fathers houſe, vvho haue bread in aboundance, vvhile I lye ſtaruing herevvith hunger? I vvill therfor goe to my father, and ſay vnto him, Father I haue
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:34305:100"/>offended againſt heauen, and againſt thee: nor am I vvorthy to be called thy ſonne: treate me onely as one of thy hyrelings.</hi> This was all the rhetoricke he vſed: to witt a true acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his owne miſerie and offences: and the plentie which was found in his fathers houſe. And ſo tooke a pious reſolution, with the harte of a contrite, and humbled child, to returne to a gracious father, and confeſſe his fault, willing for his punishment, to looſe the title of a ſonne, for that of a poore hirelinge.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Thus it is, my ſoule, that we ought to enter into our ſelues, by comparing the honour and plentie which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed in our fathers houſe,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:34305:101"/>where a quiete conſcience, heauenly comforts, benedic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and graces doe abounde; with the diſaſters, diſgrace, and abandonments which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience made vs find and feel, when like fugitiues we wandred abroad, and were reduced at length, to that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of miſerie, as to feede with ſwine. Thus it is that we are to returne home againe, by an humble confeſſion of our faults to God, and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: hartily acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that we are noe longer worthy of that noble Title of domeſtikes of God, ſonns of God, coheires, and ſpouſes of Chriſt, but onely of poore hirelings, which we willingly imbrace. Thus doe my ſoule, and we shall infallibly be
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:34305:101"/>receiued into the open bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of a tender father, whoſe bowells are more prone to mercy, then our miſerable harts readie to craue it as we ought.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Hovv vve are to returne to God, by the example of <hi>B.</hi> Marie Magdalene.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that that mirour of true penitents returned to God in the beſt manner ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, that is, with humilitie and loue mixed with teares, &amp;c. <hi>Vt cognouit,</hi> ſaith the Euangeliſt, <hi>as ſoone as she knevv that Ieſus vvas ſett dovvne,</hi> to table <hi>in the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies houſe</hi> &amp;c. she entred with a pious impudence, where she
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:34305:102"/>was not inuited and placed her ſelfe, behind him at his feete, she began to water his feete with teares, and wiped them with the haires of her heade, and kiſſed them &amp;c. She delayed not; to witt, <hi>the grace of the holie Ghoſt knovves noe ſluggish delay.</hi> She blushed not: becauſe the confuſion which she felt within, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her, that outward shame was not to be valued. She ſpoke not, where she knew that the language of a contrite harte was better heard, and her teares, the while, more effectually ſpoke her errand. So that she wrought her wrothfull Iudge, to turne her pious Aduocate, and to pronounce a fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence for her. <hi>Thy
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:34305:102"/>ſinns are forgiuen thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Theſe indeede, my ſoule, are the bliſſed diſpoſitions, which leade vs to a perfect reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with God. But alas! who is ſo impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proude as to preſume to haue them without his gifte who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them, aſſuring vs by S. Iohn, <hi>that vvithout him, vve can doe nothinge</hi> Say there-for; giue ô Lord, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, what thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt, <hi>that I may loue thee, as much as I deſire, and as much as dutie obliges me to.</hi> Giue humilitie, that inſeparable companion of Charitie, and ſure Guardien of virginitie. Giue, finally fountaines of teares, that day and night I may bewaile my offences:
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34305:103"/>giue them, I ſay, becauſe without thee we are able to doe nothing. Noe: for if with B. Magdalene we come to Chriſt, it is becauſe his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father drawes vs. If the deepe inwarde ſenſe of our crymes make vs inſenſible (with her) of all outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion which they bringe with them; it is <hi>the ſorrovv vvhich is accordinge to God,</hi> and from God, that workes it in our hartes. If we washe his feere with teares; it is God who powres downe that heauenly dewe. If we loue him, it is becauſe he loued vs firſt. And yet, (ô ineffable goodneſſe and benignitie!) by theſe his owne gifts he drawes vs to him, and then crownes the ſame by his free pardon,
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:34305:103"/>ſaying: <hi>thy ſinns are forgiuen thee.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>A Prayer.</head>
                           <p>Grant, ô Lord, we beſeech thee, that the worke of thy mercy may direct our hartes; becauſe with out thee; we are not able to pleaſe thee, <hi>per Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum.</hi> Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>Other Prayers.</head>
                           <p>O almightie and eternall Father, daigne, by the merits of the life and paſſion of thy onely beloued ſonne, deeply to imprinte in our hartes, true ſorrow to haue offended thee, meerely out of the motiues of loue: for alas, if we auoyde ſinne onely out of feare of Hell fire, we feare not to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, but to burne: nor are we iuſtified therby, ſince <hi>it is
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:34305:104"/>not feare of punishment, but loue of iuſtice; vvhich makes vs iuſt in thy ſight,</hi> ô Lord.</p>
                           <p>Grant me alſo, deare Lord, a perfect deteſtation of ſinne, and a firme reſolution to auoyde it here-after (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſuch and ſuch thinges which I am moſt ſubiect to, and ſtand moſt guiltie of in thy ſight.) euen purely for thyne owne goodneſſe ſake, who art infinitly worthy of the loue of all thy creatures.</p>
                           <p>Grant me finally, a true contempt of the world, and a willing flight from it, and all its pompes and vanities (which are the diuells weapons to deſtroye vs) and therby faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acquitt my ſelfe of the ſolemne promiſes made in my baptiſme. Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:34305:104"/>
                  <head>A SPIRITVALL EXERCISE before profeſſion.</head>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. <hi>The Preparitorie prayer.</hi> Veni Creator. <hi>and</hi> Deus qui corda &amp;c.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>ONSIDER that ſince now the yeare of your nouishippe, or tryall, is come to an end; and that by Gods ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace and aſſiſtance, (to his honour and glorie, and the
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:34305:105"/>good of your ſoule) you haue conceiued a generous reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſett vpon the building of the Euangelicall Towre, you are highly concerned maturely to examine how it is to be done. Nor can you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede more ſecurely then by taking it from the mouth of Prime Truth, <hi>ſaying:</hi> 
                           <q>which of you mynding to build a tower, doth not firſt ſitt downe and reckon the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are neceſſaire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he haue to finish it, leaſt that after he hath layd the foundation, and is not able to finish it, all that ſee it begin to mocke him, ſaying this man began to build, and he could not finish it.</q> You ought therfor to conſider the ſtrength of your body: the
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:34305:105"/>bent of your mynde; the motiues which brought you hither: that ſo you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, whether your body be not in truth too infirme: your mynd too weake and waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: your motiues too light, and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderate; out of ſome diſguſt, rather then a diſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted choyce: out of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of your owne abilitie and ſtrength rather then Gods inſpirations and dependance of his grace.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. Let this be done, my ſoule, in ſinceritie and truth; with grauitie and care; ſtill taking your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells with God, and from God. It is not a childs play you are going about but the worke of a perfect man. Your choyce is not for a day, but for life. The
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:34305:106"/>conſequence of it not for a tearme of ſome fewe yeares, but for eternitie, eternitie, my ſoule. In thinges, in a manner, indifferent, the choyce is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. In ſuch things of ſmale importance, it litle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes whether this, or that be done: ſo either of them be done to Gods glorie, God is pleaſed, and we merite: If we should ſtand a waighing Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, ſaith B. Sales, trading would proue too troubleſome, Marrie, goes on the ſame, the choyce of ones vocation: the propoſition of a matter of great conſequence: a worke of much difficultie &amp;c. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a ſerious ponderation, that Gods will (which is our dutie happineſſe and perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) may be diſcerned therin.
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:34305:106"/>And let our firme reſolutions be made accordingly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider with what it is that this Euangelicall Towre, or ſpirituall building ought to be built, and S. Auguſtine will teach you, <hi>that it is to be done vvith noe other treaſure, then the forſaking of all, and follovving of Chriſt,</hi> which he takes from Truth it ſelfe, ſaying; <hi>Euery one of you that doth not renounce all that he hath can not be my Diſciple.</hi> And the ſame Truth expreſſes what he meanes <hi>by renounceing of all,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>If any man come to me, and hateth not his Father and mother, and vvife, and children, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and ſiſters, yea and his
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:34305:107"/>evvne life beſides, he cannot be my Diſciple.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION. This, my ſoule, is the conctition of the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation into which we are to enter, for the building of this ſpirituall Towre. This muſt be performed by vs, and euen by all Chriſtians in generall (at leaſt in perparation of mynde) or els in vaine doe we pretend to be the Diſciples, or ſeruants of Chriſt. Giue all, and gayne all. At any leſſe coſte, this ſpirituall Towre will not be finished: at any leſſe rate the Euangelicall pearle will not be purchaced. Vnleſſe all this be performed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaith Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>You cannot be my Diſciples:</hi> you cannot be true Religious and true followers of Chriſt. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:34305:107"/>this generous reſolution be abſolutley vndertaken: let our deſigne be abſolutly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken. To ſerue God by halues, will proue vnproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to vs, God deſires the hart which was made by himſelfe, and for himſelfe, and he will haue it whole. The virgines whole thoughtes, and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes ought to be imployed <hi>vpon the thinges vvhich per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to our Lord: that she may be holy both in body and in ſpirit.</hi> Remember that it was S. Paule who ſaith it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="214" facs="tcp:34305:108"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. MEDITATION<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> FOR THE FIRST DAY.</hi> Of the ſolide and ſure fundation of this ſpirituall building.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider what fundation ought to be layd to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte this waightie, and moſt important building; and your holy Father will tell you againe, that it ought to be noe other then humilitle. Doe you, ſaith he, pretende to erecte a fabrike of a huge highth? Thinke firſt of the foundation, humilitie. And by how much higher we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to rayſe the building, and to charge more waight
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:34305:108"/>vpon it, by ſo much deeper we muſt digge the fundation. Now, vnto what a vaſte highth is the toppe of our Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelliall Towre to reach? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes euen into the ſight of God, that great God, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſe and dreadfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. How vaſtly deepe then ought our foundation to be digged?</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Yes my ſoule: it is euen into the ſight of this dreadfull Maieſtie, that we intend that the toppe of our Towre should reach. That maieſtie, which the Angells prayſe, the Dominations adore, the Powers tremble at; the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubins and Seraphins with dreade ſinge to. <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> for euer. Let vs not
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:34305:109"/>hazard ſo hugely important a peece vpon vnſound ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes which will proue at length but ruines. Nay, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, let vs digge quite through, this looſe earth of which we are made, <hi>exinanite exinanite vſques ad fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in-ea.</hi> Let vs neuer leaue digging till we meete without owne nothinge; till we knowe it certainly; till we confeſſe it ingenuouſly: that, is our ſafeſt ground to build vpon. where we may iuſtly hope that God will put a hand too, and rayſe the worke; ſince his cuſtome is, to trade vpon nothinge and to worke wonders vpon it. All my ſoule, may we be ſo truly nothing in our owne eyes, <hi>that he vvho is potent, may looke vpon our abiectneſſe,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:34305:109"/>and doe great thinges in vs.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> What this foundation (humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie) is.</head>
                        <p>Conſider what humilitie truly is; and you will receiue from your holy Father, that it is a <hi>voluntarie ſtooping, or lovving of the mynde, out of a ſerious conſideration of vvhat our almightie maker is, and vvhat vve are in relation to him.</hi> Or againe; <hi>humilitie is a vertue vvherby a man vvaxeth vile in his ovvne ſight, by the true Knovvledge he hath of his ovvne miſerie.</hi> Or els from S. Bernard: <hi>Humilitie is veritie;</hi> that is the truth of what God is, and what is man; which being well knowne and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:34305:110"/>it is impoſſible but that our hartes should bowe downe to the verie ground, and keepe vs there with our mouthes in the duſt wherof we were made.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. Now, my ſoule, if humilitie be nothinge els but a ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the harte vpon the knowledge we haue, of what God is, and what we are, let our conſideration be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually fixed vpon thoſe two thinges, as the ſure, ſolide, and true ground therof; ſaying with the humble S. Francis. O my God, Who art thou, and who am I? Who art thou, but an immenſe, inacceſſible, ineffable, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Maieſtie? And who am I, but a miſerable,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:34305:110"/>inconſiderable, contemptible abiſſe of miſerie? Who art thou, but an infinite rich Maſter, who canſt neede no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge that is myne? And who am I, but a poore, needie, beggarly ſeruant, who am conſtrayned to begge breade at thy dore euery day? Who art thou, but à permanent, independant, eternall eſſence or being? And who am I, as the ſcriptures teach, but <hi>a vapor, a morning devve, a drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, a fantome, a fading flovver, a pure vanitie, a blaſt of vvinde, as had ovve,</hi> in aword, a thinge, which neither hath any other thinge, more miſerably poore, or more vainely proude then it ſelfe. <hi>Duſt and ashes, then, vvhy art thou proude?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="220" facs="tcp:34305:111"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE SECONDE DAY. <hi>Of vvhom vve ought to learne humilitie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider of whom you ought to learne humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and S. Auguſtine will tell you, that he ſends you not to publicans and harlots, who yet will be preferred before the proude perſon in the Kingdome of heauen, but to the Kinge of heauen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who cryes out as it were in a publick auditorie of all man kinde: <hi>come vnto me, and learne of me.</hi> But tell me; I beſeech thee, ſaith he, ô thou
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:34305:111"/>ſonne of God, what muſt I learne of thee, by coming to thee? <hi>that I am mylde, and humble in harte.</hi> Are then all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge which are hidd in thee, reduced to this, that we muſt learne this of thee, as ſome great matter of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>that thou art mylde and humble in harte?</hi> Is it ſo great a thinge to become litle, that vnleſſe we learne it of thee, who art ſo great, we shall neuer be able to learne it? Yes truly, ſaith he, euen ſo it is: for the peace and repoſe of the ſoule can be noe otherwiſe attained to, then by diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that vnrulie ſwelling, which makes a man ſeeme great in his owne eyes, while he appeares vnſound in thyne, ôn; Lord.</p>
                        <pb n="222" facs="tcp:34305:112"/>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. We are here called to Chriſts ſchoole, my ſoule, to learne a a leſſon which the world was neuer acquainted with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The great Rabbys of the Lawe looked ouer it, to finde the firſt places in the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue. The learned Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers vnderſtoode it not, and thence vanished in their owne wiſdome. The great Potenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the earth looked vpon it with ſcorne, and thence they <hi>vvere throvvne dovvne from their ſeates.</hi> But the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Maſter of it, and will haue vs to learne of him: not to create newe worlds; not to make viſible and inuiſible things; not to worke miracles, and raiſe the deade &amp;c. which
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:34305:112"/>we should haue iudged a ſtrange, ſince an impoſſible commande, but this onely, short, ſweete and eaſie leſſon; <hi>myldneſſe and humilitie of harte.</hi> For alas, without it, what would it profite vs to be able to ſay, as ſome shall ſay to God: did we not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in thy name? did we not eaſt our Diuells? did we not worke many wonders? What would it profit vs, I ſay: ſince we should onely heare with them: <hi>I knovv you not; be gone from me, ô you vvorkers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that it is noe wonder that the teaching of humilitie, was one of his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſermons to all mankind in earth, ſince, as it may ſeeme,
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:34305:113"/>one of his wiſdomes cheife deſignes in coming downe from heauen, was to teache the ſonnes of earth that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie way to heauen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that <hi>none aſcends but he vvho deſcends.</hi> To witt he had ſeene one of the brighteſt of his ſtarrs with huge multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of his accurſed crue rushe downe to Hell, by their proude ambition of aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: and therfor he would reache the earth by deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to aſcende aboue the Heauens. They loſt their right to Heauen by aſpiring aboue their places, to more then they were; and man was to be taught to cure contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by contraries, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intitle himſelfe to heauen, by humbly ſtaying in his place,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:34305:113"/>and by remayning what he was, by dwelling in his poore naked nothing; which alone (were it anything) he might properly tearme his owne.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If the verie brighteſt ſtarrs fall from Heauen, where pride can gett noe ſafe footing; what ought we poore wormes to doe in earth but feare, and keepe our ſelues within the compaſſe of what we are? If they fell to Hell by aſpiringe to be like to the higheſt; let our firme reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and whole ſtrife be, to aſcende to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by affecting to be equall to, or euen leſſe then the loweſt: ſince Thruth hath ſaid it, nor can he deceiue vs: <hi>that he vvho exaltes himſelfe shall be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and be that humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:34305:114"/>shall be exalted.</hi> Nay, my ſoule, ſince the ſame Truth comes to teach vs this leſſon in his ſacred paſſion, let vs not proue ſo much contrarie to his bleſſed deſigne, and our owne aduantage, as not to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to learne it, with the whole ſtrife of our hartes. Howbeit, ſith he is as well the teacher, as giuer of it, let vs often ſay with S. Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine: <hi>thou commandeſt humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, ô Lord, giue vvhat thou commandeſt, and commande vvhat thou vvilt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="227" facs="tcp:34305:114"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION. FOR THE 2. DAY.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that hence it was, that the diuine wiſdome, or Word of God, which was in the begining with God; nay, was God (and therfor could thinke it noe ſtealth to be coequall, coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, conſubſtantiall with God the Father) exinanited, or powred himſelfe out, and became flesh, <hi>Et Verbum caro factum eſt,</hi> taking vpon him the shape of a ſeruant. Earth is at a loſſe, vpon this abiſmall humiliation, litle kowing, as faith S. Auguſtine, what to ſay to it, or what conceipt to
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:34305:115"/>make of it. Nay the heauenly powers ſtand amayſed, to ſea the kinge of Angells, become leſſe then the Angells: yee iuſt like to one of vs (in all thinges ſaue ſinne) nay one of vs indeede: <hi>flesh of our flesh: bones of our bones,</hi> poore man. Vnleſſe we should yet ſay further, leſſe then man: <hi>Nouiſsimus virorum, the leaſt and laſt of men: a vvorme and not a man,</hi> with the royall Prophete.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. Ah my poore ſoule; if the gracious inuitations, and mylde leſſons of Wiſdome cannot preuayle to plucke downe our proude harte; let at leaſt the abiſmall example of our humaniſed God, the eternall Word made flesh
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:34305:115"/>put before our eyes, diſſipate, and cure that pernicious tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. It is thy verie God that lyes humbled at thy feete my ſoule; it is diuinitie it ſelfe, which lyes, as it were, infirme before thee, that ſo thy ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling being worne downe, thou mightſt deiect thy ſelfe, and caſte thy ſelfe proſtrate, vpon that great God, <hi>Deus Deorum,</hi> now, for thy example, become the laſt and leaſt of men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE II. POINTE.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that if this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly deſigne, and reſolution be truly admirable; farre, farre aboue the reach of men and Angells, and the execution of it, ineffably gracious, and euen rauishinge (as ſpeaking more ſweetneſſe, and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:34305:116"/>delightes to humane hartes, then they are any way capable to comprehende; ſo that they doe not ſo much intice, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the ſaid hartes to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, if there be any ſenſe of man left in man) ſo the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable circumſtances which accompaignie it, doe power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preach the ſame leſſons to the eyes of the world. If then it hath pleaſed him, to build himſelfe a cottage of the ſame claye wherof he made vs; he will alſo haue all the reſt ſuted to it. This moſt humble, Loue, metamorſiſed-kinge, will haue an humble mother Queene, <hi>a poore hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayde of our Lord,</hi> An humble putatiue father, <hi>Ioſeph a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter.</hi> An humble Pallace, a poore: <hi>Rocke or caue.</hi> An hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:34305:116"/>chaire of ſtate, <hi>a manger</hi> Humble attendants, <hi>an oxe and an Aſſe, vvith a fevve ſillie shephardes:</hi> and after that, all his life longe, poore, rude, <hi>ſimple fishermen.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. What, my ſoule; will be euer able to decrye pride, if this doe not? And what will be able to imprinte humilitie deepe in the verie bottomes of our hartes, if this proue not effectuall? His poore, abiect, and deſpicable condition, in the verie firſt ſteppe he made into this world began to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish it: His lowlie, obſcure, and hidden life, all the tyme of his infancie, declared it: in his riper yeares he continually preached it: the courſe of his whole life, confirmed it: and
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:34305:117"/>at his death, he ſigned it with his pretious, bloude, <hi>humbling himſelfe to death, and the death of the croſſe,</hi> the moſt infamous of all deathes. O my ſoule, let vs then, being forced by all theſe preſſing, and euen oppreſſing arguments, either humble our ſelues to the ground in all occaſions of humiliation; or at leaſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to our confuſion, that we are the moſt vnworthy, and vnſutable ſeruants, to a diuine Maſter, who was in all thinges ſo incomparably humble.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="233" facs="tcp:34305:117"/>
                     <head>THE I. MEDITATION FOR THE THIRD DAY. <hi>Of the Benefit of a religious vocation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that it ſeemed not enough to that Kinge of glorie, Firſt to haue made you a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, after his owne likeneſſe, and all the other creatures for your vſe. 2. to haue regenerated you to a new and better life by the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme. 3. to haue giuen you the knowledge of the Catholike faith, hauing culled you out of multitudes that daylie perish: but his
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:34305:118"/>gracious beneuolence went yet further on with you, and by this holie vocation to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, called you to be his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar friend and ſeruant and Fauourite, to haue a more neere and deare conuerſation with him, and to make it your buſineſſe in earth, to ſinge his prayſes, and mercyes, as the Bleſſed shall doe for euer and euer in Heauen.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O the infinite goodneſſe of my deare Lord who goes ſtill on, in my behalfe, heaping benefit vpon benefit, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours vpon fauours; yea fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of ſingular preference, tender loue, and greateſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; towards the attayning of Beatitude, that can be mette with vpon this perilous
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:34305:118"/>ſea. Fauours not granted to all, nay ſcarce to a few, among multitudes who daylie ſuffer shipwracke; while thy free grace, deare God, not my merits, hath guided my doubtfull nauigation to a ſafe harbour. Where (witneſſe S. Bernard who experienced the ſame) one liues more pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, falls more rarely, riſeth more quicklie, walkes more cautiouſly, receiues grace more frequently, repoſeth more ſecurely, dyes more confidently, and is rewarded more abundantly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> That this vocation leads to a certaine ſtate.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:34305:119"/>by meanes of this holie vocation, lendes you not to a certaine indifferencie of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, or not ſeruing him, at your owne pleaſure and election; but he bringes you therby to a ſetled and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſtate, wherin your body is tyed to ſtabilitie in a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne place; and all your actions are marked out, and limited by Rule and conſtitutions, and all theſe confirmed by the three eſſential vowes of Religion, Pouertie, chaſtitie and obedience, <hi>according to S. Auguſtins Rule.</hi> Which vowes are noe other things then ſacred and ſolemne promiſes freely, deliberatly, and with out conſtrainte, made to God in the face of the holy Church, of thinges which are
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:34305:119"/>better, as S. Thomas of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne teacheth.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. This, my ſoule, was Gods ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular goodneſſe to vs, to winne our hartes by our owne free choyce, to renounce that dangerous libertie, which might happly haue proued our ruine, to imbrace the true libertie of the children of God, which is neuer ſo free, or euen truly free indeede, but vnder the ſeruitude of that moſt pious Kinge of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, according to that of S. Auguſtine; <hi>Libertie is neuer greater then vnder a pious Kinge,</hi> whom to ſerue, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede to raigne: and <hi>happie is that bleſſed neceſsitie vvhich compells vs to the better.</hi> Our falſe libertie then is turned
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:34305:120"/>into a neceſſitie, but it is to be truly free: to haue nothing common with the world: not to be tortured with the greedie deſire of vaine toyes! to haue noe commerce with wickedneſſe: to paſſe our tyme in innocencie. Our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are noe more ours: noe, but they are gaynfully ſpent vpon the purchace of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Heauen. The diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of our body is not in our owne hands: true, but it is to imitate the Angells. The goods of our mynd, our verie will is at anothers diſpoſe. Yes, but it is, that by wanting it for a tyme, we may inioy it for an eternitie.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="239" facs="tcp:34305:120"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE THIRD DAY. <hi>Of the vovve of pouertie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that if humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be the baſis and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which ſecures all that is built vpon it, pouertie muſt be at the charges to rayſe the walls. But with what treaſure will pouertie performe this worke? Marrie with noe other, as S. Auguſtine hath told vs, but with relinquish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all we either haue or can hope for. So is the toppe and perfection of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall building to be attained to; as wiſdome it ſelfe aſſures
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:34305:121"/>vs, ſaying: if thou wilt be perfect, <hi>goe and ſell all that thou haſt, and giue it to the poore, and take vp thy croſſe and come and follovv me.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. O glorious and rich pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which alone art able to vndertake and accomplish ſo great a worke. The riches of a kingdome are ſcarcely ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to finish one princely Louure: and yet the pouertie of one poore free giuing harte, is able to rayſe a ſtately Towre reaching into the ſight of God, and to poſſeſſe it ſelfe of his kingdome. O gaynfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce! ô diuine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-rich trading! Ingenious pouertie is able to improue her ſmale talent, to an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred-fold aduantage: and to
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:34305:121"/>the ſure poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting. He ſayes it, whom we dare not miſbeleeue: <hi>euery one that hath left houſe, or landes for my names ſake, shall receiue an hundred fold, and shall poſſeſſe life euerlaſting.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINT.</hi> That Euangelicall pouertie ought to be learnt of Chriſt.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Phyloſophers both pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and in ſome ſort practiſed pouertie, as not reputing him worthy of God who did not dontemne riches: yea and ſome among them qualified it <hi>laeta paupertas,</hi> ioyfull po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie. Yet hardly should we either haue taſted the ioy of it, or haue put our ſelues to
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:34305:122"/>the practiſe therof, had we not had a better Maſter to haue propoſed it to vs by way of counſell; preached it to vs with a bliſſing vpon it; and practiſed it in his owne ſacred perſon all his life longe: who being rich became poore to inrich vs by his owne pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. He was poore in his nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie; being borne in a poore caue or ſtable; wrapped vp in poore clothes; layd on a poore locke of hay, lodged in a poore manger, accompai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned with a poore oxe and aſſe. All the courſe of his life was ſpent in pouertie and want: neuer hauing any poſſeſſion, noe not ſo much as a place to shrude his heade, and at his death he was ſtript naked vpon the croſſe.</p>
                        <pb n="243" facs="tcp:34305:122"/>
                        <p>AFFECTION. and RESOLVT. And yet, was he not eternall prouidence, and foreſawe all this? Was he not eternall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſo could haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented it all? Was he not the riches of heauen, and our God, who could ſtand in want of nothing that is ours? Conclude then my ſoule, with much ioy and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? either are we making a good choyce of this poore life we intende to leade; or els the wiſdome of heauen may ſeeme to haue miſt in his choyce. But wiſdome could not deceiue, nor be deceiued: reioyce then, my ſoule, to haue made ſo ſure, ſo happie, ſo Chriſt like a choyce. And let vs neuer ceaſe to vſe our vttermoſt endeuours, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:34305:123"/>his extreame pouertie in his natiuitie, in his life, and at his death.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE 4. DAY.</hi> To vvhat this vovve of pouertie doth abſolutly binde vs.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that the pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to which you oblidge your ſelfe, is accordinge to S. Auguſtins Rule. That is, not to mendicitie, not to penurie, or extreame want of neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in meate drinke or clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes &amp;c. But to poſſeſſe what you poſſeſſe in common, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Apoſtolicall and primitiue Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:34305:123"/>in the fourth of the Actes: <hi>All thinges vvere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vnto them</hi> &amp; <hi>neither vvas there any needie among them</hi> &amp; <hi>and to euerie one vvas deuided, according as euery one had neede.</hi> From theſe bleſſed firſt fruites of Chriſtianitie, did your holy father, as himſelfe declares, take the model of your life. So that, as you can haue nothing of your owne, nor euen the power to call it ſo: ſo on the other ſide, you haue right to your share in the comon diſtribution of the whole.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. How happie are we, my ſoule, to haue fixed vpon ſo happie a proceeding; where we are neither to haue nor want ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: to witt we neither ſuffer
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:34305:124"/>the danger of hauing them; not the incommoditie of wanting them. Happie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which frees vs from the perill of riches, which makes the way of heauen almoſt impoſſible: and yet ſubiects vs not to the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, of the want of them, wherby life becomes loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and neceſſitie compells to vnworthy and baſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. This golden meane, was certainly the production of the holy Ghoſt in thoſe boylinge primitiue hartes, whence it was deriued downe to vs; and wherby we can ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pronounce with the Apoſtle: <hi>vve haue nothinge, and yet vve poſſeſſe all thinges,</hi> by the harmeleſſe vſe which we are permitted to make of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="247" facs="tcp:34305:124"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> What pouertie a true Religious ought indeede to ayme at.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that though the poſſeſſing of nothing in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or want of proprietie. be all that you canonically promiſſe or are bound to; yet your aymes indeede, are the contempt of riches, and of the verie deſire of them. It is not gold and ſiluer that the Apoſtle tearmes the roote of all euil, <hi>but the inordinate coueting of them.</hi> Nor are rich perſons alone ſubiect to dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>but theſe alſo that couet to be riche, vvho,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>fall into snares, and temptations.</hi> The pouertie which our ſauiour preacheth with a benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <pb n="248" facs="tcp:34305:125"/>vpon it, is ſpirituall pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or pouertie of the d'iſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſt mynde which neither has them, nor cares for them, nor ſeekes the commodities and pleaſures they bringe with them, further then a meere neceſſarie liuelyhoode, as we ſee in our B. Sauiours example, which is our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne indeede.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. The actuall want of riches, my ſoule, and the banishing of thoſe contentious words <hi>myne and thyne,</hi> is a good ſteppe to beatitude: ſince therby innumerable occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of contentions and quarrells are cut off. Yet alas, that is not all that the ſpouſes of Chriſt should ayme at who in their pouertie ought to
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:34305:125"/>expreſſe the pouertie of Chriſt, who neither had them, nor deſired them, nor the commodities and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights which accompanie them. It profits vs not at all, ſaith S. Caeſarius, to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donne riches outwardly, vnleſſe we roote out withall the inward deſire of them, which ſticke cloſe to our hartes. It is not too much, my ſoule, for poore naked man, to follow poore and naked Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE 4. DAY. <hi>Of the vovve of chaſtitie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>COnſider, that if humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie hath placed the
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:34305:126"/>foundation, and pouertie rayſed the walls, chaſtitie woud be at the coſt to a dorne it within: for it is indeede Virginitie that is the begining of ſpirituall beautie and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament. <hi>All the beautie and glorie of the Kings daugher is vvithin.</hi> Yea ſaith S. Bernarde, virginitie is the beſt, and moſt wishfull furniture, and ſuch as might euen proue a kind of enuie to the Angells themſelues, which though otherwiſe Virgines too; yet are they not virgines inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with flesh and bloud: whereas to liue in flesh and not according to flesh, is not an earthly, but a heauenly life, ſaith S. Hierome.</p>
                     <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. With what other ornament,
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:34305:126"/>my ſoule, then virginall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, was that royall Hall, or earthly Paradice, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, which was to receiue the puritie of heauen, which came downe to eſpouſe mans nature? If virginall puritie then was to giue intertayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the ſonne of God in earth, noe wonder, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie too muſt adorne the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall building which we are rayſing vp into the ſight of God in heauen. Let vs not fayl, my ſoule, to put an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable price vpon this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall vertue, which heauen ſo highly values. It being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede the iuery Throne which the heauenly ſalomon built for himſelfe. And let vs neuer eſteeme it ſafe but onely vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> its ſure foundation humilitie.</p>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="252" facs="tcp:34305:127"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE SECONDE POINTE.</hi> That by the vovve of chaſtitie you are truly maried to God.</head>
                        <p>Conſider to what a highth of dignitie you are admitted by this heauenly vowe: certes to noe leſſe then an abſolute mariage with God. So were we taught by Tortullian 14. hundred yeares agoe; ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to a virgine: <hi>thou art maried to Chriſt: to him didſt thou deliuer vp thy body: to him thou didſt betrouth thy maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Walke on then, according to thy ſpouſe his vvill and pleaſure.</hi> Whence the Church of God till this day, appoints theſe words to be ſaid at your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the veyle: <hi>receiue this ſacred veyle, vvherby you
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:34305:127"/>may be knovvne to haue contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the vvorld; and to haue ſubiected or eſpouſed your ſelfe for euer to Chriſt the spouse of virgines.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL.</p>
                        <p>O admirable dignitie of the Virgine, where the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hand may de is rayſed to the honour of a Bride to Chriſt himſelfe, the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome! whom when she loues, she's chaſte: whom when she touches, she's pure: whom when she takes in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, she is a virgine! O ſuperceleſtiall mariage! from whence fidelitie, and fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie are expected, as well as in other mariages: becauſe ſuch as breake the firſt faith, <hi>haue damnation,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Yea, the happie ſtate of vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines,
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:34305:128"/>aſſures S. Auguſtine, is more fruitfull and fertile; not by hauing great bellies, but great myndes: not by hauing breaſts full of mylke, but hartes full of candour: and in lieu of binging forth earth out of their bowells, by bringing forth heauen by their prayers. Hence iſſues a noble progenie; puritie, iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, patience, myldneſſe, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie attended by all herno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble traine of vertues; the holy virgins heauenly iſſue.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="255" facs="tcp:34305:128"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE 5. DAY. <hi>Of the vovve of obedience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the ground worke, is ſure: that riche pouertie hath rayſed the walles, and ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall puritie hath adorned the worke interiourly, Yet muſt tranſcendante bedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſecure all, or nothinge will proue ſtable. All is ſure in obedience, all without it is in danger. Obedience, ſaith your holy Father, is, as it were, the mother, and keeper of all: she continually
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:34305:129"/>watches that noe parte of our ſpirituall building may be lyable to any danger. And this ſo neceſſarie vertue of obedience, is nothing els but <hi>a voluntarie and rationall ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of our ovvne vvill</hi> to the will of another, which S. Iohn Climacus tearmes, <hi>the death or graue of our ovvne vvill.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If then, my ſoule, our greateſt aſſurance be found in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, let our greateſt care be imployed to purchace, conſerue, and practiſe it. <hi>By obeying our Superiours, it is</hi> (ſaith S. Gregorie) <hi>that God is obedient to our prayers.</hi> And your holy Father, dares affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me; <hi>that one prayer of an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient perſon is ſooner heard,
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:34305:129"/>thet ten thousand of one diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient.</hi> It is obedience which makes vs ſecure: obedience which frees vs from care and ſollicitude: Obedience which renders our meate, drinke, and play, meritorious. By obedience we equally aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce our iorney towards heauen in ſtanding ſtill, as walking on; in ſleeping as wakinge. O admirable aduantages of obedience! O how happie and ſecure is the condition of an obedient ſoule, of whom the wiſeman pronounceth <hi>that she shall ſinge victories.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> That obedience is the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant of the three vovves.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that though the
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:34305:130"/>vowes of pouertie and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, contribute much to the happie ſtate of a religious life, yet doth that of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience farre excelle them, and in ſome ſorte conteynes them all, according to the ſenſe of the Angelicall Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour. For wheras Religion is a ſacrifice, wherin pouertie offers all her goods of Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne; and chaſtitie all thoſe of the body: obedience goes yet further, and ſacryficeth all thoſe of the mynde, as ſelfe-will, ſelfe-iudgement, and euen the whole man, which certainly is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably more excellent then all the reſt.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Pouertie, and chaſtitie, ſaith S. Bernard, are the two winges
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:34305:130"/>by which obedience mounts aloft. Yet it is she indeede, not they that flye. A douzen ſuch winges would not be able to rayſe proude diſobedience one inch to heauen-wards. It is neither our goods of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, nor thoſe of our body, which will proue a pleaſing ſacry fice in the ſight of God, vnleſſe they be accompayned with obedience, the humble ſubmiſſion of the will, and iudgement. <hi>Banishe out of your harte, this pleaſeth, and this displeaſeth,</hi> ſaith your brother a Kempis, <hi>and nothing shall trouble you.</hi> and S. Bernarde, <hi>take avvay the vvill, and there shall be noe hell.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="260" facs="tcp:34305:131"/>
                     <head>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE 5. DAY. <hi>Of the extent of obedience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider, that as to make obedience abſolutly blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, were to depriue man of man, that is, of reaſon wherby he is differenced from a beaſt, and to oppoſe that of the Apoſtle; <hi>let your obſeruance be reaſonable:</hi> ſo to leaue it wholy to the guidance, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of reaſon; were rather to make a man a Phyloſopher, then either a good religious perſon, or euen a good Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. It muſt ſo farre ſee, as to be able to diſcerne Gods part,
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:34305:131"/>becauſe the Decree is without exception, <hi>that vve ought rather to obeye God then men.</hi> But where we doe not manifestly ſee, that Gods right is tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vpon, or violated, we ought abſolutly to obeye a ſuperiours commande in all things without reſerue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is ſuperiour. And this kind of obedience falls vnder your vowe, and is abſolutly neceſſarie.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOLV. O my ſoule, if our owne reaſon were made the Rule of our obedience, with what confuſions, and endleſſe wranglings would not Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries be replenished? They would not ſo much be found ſacred and ſilent ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as cententious Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies.
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:34305:132"/>It is at the death of our rebellious wills (that peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſource of mans miſerie and mortall poiſon of a ſpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life) that obedience aymes, which is not effected by proude diſputes, but by humble ſubmiſſions; hauing continually in mynd <hi>that all povver is from God, and he vvho reſiſts povver reſiſts Gods ordonnance.</hi> Let vs then, my ſoule, humbly and promptly obeye God in our ſuperiours perſon, ſtanding alwayes in a bliſſed indifferencie with S. Paule, to heare him by their mouthes, and to obeye him, in their perſons, ſaying: <hi>What is thy holy vvill I should doe?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="263" facs="tcp:34305:132"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Of the diuers degrees of it.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that tho neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie obedience to which you are tyed by vowe, conſiſts in obeying Superiours co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands, according to Rule and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or what conduces to the due obſeruance therof. Yet are not the pious ſpouſes of Chriſt to ſtoppe there, but to be ſtill ſtriuing to emulate the better gifts, and to render themſelues wholy agreeable to their diuine ſpouſe. Be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as your heauenly father is perfect ſaith our ſauiour, by endeuouring ſtill to obeye in the moſt perfect man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, which that great ſeruant of God Ruiſbrochius putts
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:34305:133"/>downe as followes. In the firſt place it muſt be prudent and diſcreete. 2. ſimple. 3. cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. 4. prompt. 5. couragious. 6. deuoute. 7. humble.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O what a bleſſed life is ledd where all theſe conditions meete! O what a Heauen appeares in earth where earthly Angells thus liue Let this be our cheife endeuour, my ſoule, as it is the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſecuritie, and ornament of a religious life. Let vs with prudence and diſcretion diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Gods will by our ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours mouth, and whether we be commanded to watch, to faſt, to pray or worke, &amp;c. or els vpon occaſions, at their pleaſure, to leaue them off, let it be done ſimply, and
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:34305:133"/>with aſſurance, that by how much more ſimply, by ſo much the more fruitfully and excellently its done. Let that diſcreete ſimplicitie be ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with quicke and chees<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full execution: <hi>for God loues a free and merrie-harted giuer.</hi> If the thinge commanded appeare hard, yet imbrace it with a manly courage, heauen is worth more, and he who gaue the commande can giue ſtrength to performe it. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, let all this be done with humilitie and deuotion, not ſo much to pleaſe men, as that our heauenly father may be glorified.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="266" facs="tcp:34305:134"/>
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE 6. DAY. <hi>Of the excellencies of Obedience.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider with deuoute Ruiſbrochius, that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is a vertue of ſo great excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, that the verie leaſt worke, be it of what kinde it will, being done by vertue therof, is much better, and more acceptable to God, then euen other geate workes done without it; as for example, hearing of Maſſe, reading, praying, contemplating, or any other worke you can thinke of. Which leſſon we
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:34305:134"/>are yet taught by a greater Maſter: Kings 1.15. <hi>Will our Lord haue Holocauſts and victi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and not rather that his voyce should be obeyd? For bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is obedience then victimes: and to harken rather, then to offer the fatt of rammes. Becauſe</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it is as it vvere the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of Idolatrie to refuſe to obey.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECT and RESO. It is not ſo much the greatneſſe of the thinge then, my ſoule, we ought to looke vpon, as the greatneſſe of the obedience with which we are to perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me it. Commandes of great and herociall actions rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occurre, wheras obedience may be daylie exerciſed, and merite increaſed in a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſmale matters: Nor is
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:34305:135"/>it eaſily to be conceiued, what riches are to be treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp for heauen therby. Deuoute obedience knowes how to render the poore wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes myte a gratfull offering. Induſtrious obedience nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiates vpon trifles, and yet like the honie bee ſtores her hyue with huge riches. Many other vertues, daughters of Charitie, gather maine hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of treaſure togeither, yet obedience ſo farre outſtripps them all, that she makes her ſelfe more gratefull to God then a ſacryfice.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> Of vvhom vve ought to learne Obedience.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that we ought to
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:34305:135"/>learne this beſt of morall vertues of the beſt of Maſters of moralitie Ieſus Ch. Who is as well the Maſter, as the Diſciple, of it. He was the Maſter of it: at his coming into the world; while he liued in it; and at his departure out of it. At his coming, S. Paule tells vs in his perſon: <hi>in the heade of the booke it is vvritten of me, that I should doe thy vvill: then ſaid I: behold I come that I may doe thy vvill o God.</hi> His whole life was ſpent in the doing the will of his heauenly father who ſent him, and in obeying his mother, S. Ioſeph, and euen all creatures for his ſake. At his departure, <hi>he vvas obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient euen vnto death, and the death of the Croſſe.</hi> And he
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:34305:136"/>was the Diſciple of it too; ſithens, as S. Paule affirmes, though he were the ſonne of God, <hi>he learnt obedience by the thinges vvhich he suffered; and vvas made the cause of eternall saluation to all that obey him.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. O what an excellent leſſon of obedience hath the ſonne of God, left for the ſonnes of men to imitate! He, who, as God, could be obedient to none, being <hi>God-man,</hi> beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes obedient to all men for his heauenly fathers ſake. All his life was a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, till by his painfull death he conſummated the great worke of mans redemption, for which he was ſent. <hi>Father</hi> I <hi>haue consummated the vvorke vvhih thou gaueſt me to doe,</hi>
                           <pb n="271" facs="tcp:34305:136"/>ſaith that intirely obedient ſonne. The worke which we are to doe, my ſoule, (which is as it were our whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) is, to obey God in our ſuperiours commandes, and by ſuch ſubmiſſion, and their care, to ſecure our bleſſed eternitie. By their eyes we beſt diſcerne: By their iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gements we moſt wiſely iudge: by their directions, and orders, we moſt ſurely walke to mans beatitude.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <pb n="272" facs="tcp:34305:137"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. MEDITATION FOR THE 6. DAY.</hi> That Charitie muſt be the roofe of this ſpirituall building.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider, that be the foundationes neuer ſo deeply digged: be the walls neuer ſo firme, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; and the interior partes neuer ſo fairely adorned: yet if the roofe be not ſutable to the reſt, and be not eſtablis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed aboue the reſt, it lyes but vſeleſſely open to receiue winds and shewres; and is vnfitt for the vſe of man: being indeede noe perfect buildinge, but onely the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:34305:137"/>or ruines therof; vpon which paſſers by looke with deriſion, and ſay: <hi>this man began to build, but could not finish the same.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. It is the end, my ſoule, that euery wiſe man acts for, without which his worke is imperfect, nor can he repoſe. Pouertie indeede ſeemes more then humane. Pure na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture knowes noe ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction. Virginitie is truly Angelicall and diuine; and is a fruite which is onely found in the boſome of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. None but a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine mother brings out vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines. Obedience directs all, ſecures all, confirmes all: and makes a fitt tabernacle for God in the harte of man; by
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:34305:138"/>banishing thence ſelfe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſelfe will. But hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly charitie; as a glorious mother, farr outſtrips them all, giues them all their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, increaſe, and perfection. For why indeede, my ſoule, did we firſt enterpriſe this holy worke, but becauſe we loue? What could be able to robbe vs of all we haue, but loue? What did wowe vs to virginall chaſtitie, but the loue of a virgine ſpouſe? What could moue men to depriue them ſelues of belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued libertie, and to liue at the diſpoſe of anothers will, but the loue of him alone, who chuſed rather to dye, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to accomplish the will of his heauenly Father? <hi>Loue then,</hi> ſaith your holy Father,
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:34305:138"/>
                           <hi>and doe vvhat thou vvilt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> That vvithout charitie nothing is done to secure our happie eternitie.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that if humilitie put the foundation of your ſpirituall Towre, it was by charities guidance and order: for as humilitie goes not without charitie, ſo charitie neuer leaues humilitie. If pouertie rayſed the walls, it was with the treaſure wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with charitie furniſhed her. If chaſtitie adorned it within: it was with the pure <hi>burning gold</hi> which she had of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Finally if obedience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and ſecured the whole worke; it was by the force she
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:34305:139"/>receiued <hi>of charitie, vvhich is as stronge as death.</hi> In a word all is from charitie, and all is for charitie.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION &amp; RESOLVT. He (S. Paule) knewe this truth, my ſoule, as certainly, as he affirmes it vndauntedly to wit; that not onely the foreſaid vertues profit vs nothinge without charitie, <hi>but euen that tho vve should haue all faith, so that vve could remoue moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: though vve should diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all our goods to be meate for the poore:</hi> finally, <hi>though vve should deliuer our bodies to bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and yet vvant charitie, it profits vs nothing.</hi> Charitie; ſaith holy S. Auguſtine, is that which diſcernes the ſonns of God from the ſonns of the Diuell. Charitie is that <hi>one
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:34305:139"/>neceſſarie thinge,</hi> which alone ſufficeth. Charitie, in a word, is that Euangelicall gemme, for which if a man should giue all his ſubſtance, he shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it as nothing. Come the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>ô come then, ô thou holy spirit, Deus Charitas, and replenish the hartes of thy faithfull, and inflame them vvith the fire of thy loue.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>THE FIRST MEDITAT. FOR THE 7. DAY. <hi>That all the vertues are loue.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that ſo true it is that nothing is done without charitie, that your holy Father makes noe diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:34305:140"/>to teach you, <hi>that vvithout charitie the reſt of the vertues are not indeede reputed vertues:</hi> nay further, that the reſt of the vertues are but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede loue and charitie, ſo, or ſo qualified. For what is humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie but charitie ſtooping, and reputing her ſelfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? What is pouertie, but charitie contemning all, and ſtripping herſelf of all: What is chaſtitie but loue preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing corruptible man from corruption of bodie and mynde? What finally obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but loue freely and reaſonably ſacrifycing vp the will of man, and making it ſupple and inclinable to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie creature.</p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. Charitie then, my ſoule, is
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:34305:140"/>that tranſcendant heauenly vertue without which there is noe true vertue at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is she which gouernes as Queene, giues life, vigour and worth to all the other vertues. He who loueth not remaynes in death. It is she who perfumes them all with the odour and ſweeeneſſe of holy loue: ſince we doe not meerely imbrace them, becauſe they are ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but rather in qualitie of thinges that are deſired, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, and beloued by God: (To diſcouer à man truly vertuous, we vſe not to inquire what he beleeues or what he hopes for, but what he loues. If earth h'es earthly: if Heauen, he's heauenly; if God, he's Godlike.) for as ſuch they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all deſirable, louing,
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:34305:141"/>and louelie. Let me loue thee, then, ô Lord, let me loue thee, and loue all other thinges which I loue and practiſe, for thee, and in thee: that my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued may be myne, and I wholie his.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE II. POINTE.</hi> That vve ought inceſſantly to deſire, and breath after charitie.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that if, as we haue ſeene, Charitie be all in all, our thoughtes ought to be ſett vpon the continuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of it. For what ought we, or doe we indeede deſire, but what euery one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to himſelfe for his end? and <hi>the end of the lavve is loue.</hi> What ought any Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deſire but the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the lawe of God, <hi>and
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:34305:141"/>the fulneſſe of the lavve is chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> Nor fares it in thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly deſires, as in vaine worldly wishes: a million of them puts not one pennie into our purſes. Wheras by the verie deſire of the loue of God, we begin to loue God indeed: and ſtill the more we deſire it, the more we loue. Yea, when this deſire waxes ſtronge and hartie, the deſire is turned into fire, and infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes the couering harte. <hi>He that deſires God vvith his vvhole harte has alreadie him vvhom</hi> he loues ſaith S. Gregorie. And S. Auguſtine: <hi>a holy deſire, is the vvhole life of a good Chriſtian.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. But alas, my poore ſoule, tho we clearely diſcerne this deſire
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:34305:142"/>to be moſt iuſt, aduantagious, and moſt worthy of a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> harte: yet we ſomtymes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue our ſelues not to be ſo happie, as euen to haue this deſire. Let vs then at leaſt ſay with the Prophete: <hi>my ſoule hath deſired, earneſtly to deſire thy</hi> iuſtifications at all tymes. Let vs not fayle to haue this deſire of deſiring, continually in our harte; ſaying with S. Au. <hi>Giue me thy ſelfe, reſtore me thy ſelfe: for vvhat is not thy verie ſelfe, is verie nothing to me.</hi> and it will happen with vs, as it did with the holie Prophete, that in theſe holy thoughtes and deſirs fire will flashe out; and ſo throughly inflame our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, that as the ſtagge thirſteth after the fountaines of fresh water, ſo shall we vehementlie
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:34305:142"/>couet, and thirſt after our good God, that drainleſſe fountaine of liuing water, which flowes into life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtnig.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="meditation">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. MEDITATION</hi> Of vvhom vve are to learne Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, tovvards one another.</head>
                     <div type="point">
                        <head>THE FIRST POINTE.</head>
                        <p>COnſider that we ought to learne this moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant leſſon, this <hi>one neceſſarie thinge,</hi> of him, who doth as well teach it, as giue it, our Sauiour Ieſus; who brought downe <hi>this ſacred fire into earth and his vvill vvas it should burne</hi> the hartes of men. And indeede, neuer did he ſeeme
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:34305:143"/>ſo peculiarly to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Maſter of any thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, as of this vertue and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. <q>
                              <hi>This is my precept,</hi> ſaid that deare maſter of ours, that you loue one another. My litle children. I giue you a new precept, that you loue one another. In this all men shall know that you are my Diſciples, if you haue loue one to another. Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I pray &amp;c. that they may be one, as we alſo are one, I in them, and thou in me.</q>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. This is the great commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, indeede, my ſoule, this Chriſts ſpeciall precept: <hi>Loue one another.</hi> this the badge by which he will haue all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to be knowne. <hi>If they
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:34305:143"/>loue one another.</hi> If we come without this wedding garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we shall be repulſed. If we knocke, not hauing this oyle of charitie in our Lampes, (wherby we may be knowne to men to be Gods Diſciples) God <hi>vvill not knovve vs;</hi> the <hi>dore vvill be shut.</hi> What thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge more wishfull, could we haue deſired to haue heard, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by affording mutuall loue and aſſiſtance to one another, (which we haue all ſuch neede of) to ſecure our ſaluation? And yet, the moſt louing, and beloued Apoſtle aſſures vs: It is <hi>the precept of our ſoueraigne Lord, and Maſter: doe this faith he and it ſufficeth. Beare one anothers burden, and ſo you shal accomplish the lavve of Chriſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="point">
                        <pb n="286" facs="tcp:34305:144"/>
                        <head>
                           <hi>THE SECONDE POINTE.</hi> Hovv vve ought to exerciſe Charitie to one another.</head>
                        <p>Conſider that this ought to be done by his example, who gaue the commande of it, and afterwards came gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly downe to teach it by his owne practiſe. Thus we are taught by the great Apoſtle. Receiue, helpe, comfort, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and loue one another as Chriſt receiued, aſſiſted, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported and loued vs. But how did Chriſt loue vs &amp;c? Marrie, he loued vs firſt, with a free, and diſintereſted loue, which looked vpon noe preceedant merites. 2. With a right loue, not to receiue any thinge from vs, but to diſcharge the
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:34305:144"/>ouer-flowing riches of his mercifull breaſtes vpon our pouertie. 3. With a perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant loue: <hi>for louing his vvho vvere in the vvorld, he loued them to the end.</hi> 4. With a ſtronge loue; euen as ſtronge as death it ſelfe: <hi>he loued vs, and deliuered himſelfe for vs: for vs men, and for our ſaluation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>AFFECTION and RESOL. If then my ſoule, we hope for any conſolation in Chriſt; if any ſolace of Charitie; if any ſocietie of ſpirit, if any bowells of commiſeration, let vs endeuour to fulfill the B. Apoſtles ioy, by being of one meaning (having the ſame charitie) of one mynd, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in one. That nothing be done by contention, nor by vaine glorie: but in humilitie;
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:34305:145" rendition="simple:additions"/>each counting others better then themſelues. In a word, let vs receiue, comfort, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and loue our poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: and that too; as Chriſt gaue vs the example, with a pure and diſinterreſted loue, becauſe it is his bleſſed plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that ſo it should be. With a right loue, <hi>not ſeeking that vvhich is profitable,</hi> in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, <hi>to our ſelues, but that vvhich is profitable to many.</hi> With a perſeuerant loue, which is not to end but with the end of our liues. Finally, with a ſtronge loue, readie to wraſtle with obuious difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and euen with death it ſelfe, for the good of our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as our deare Lord gaue vs an example.</p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:34305:145"/>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
